<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Créachta Crích Fódla</title>
        <author>Aoḋaġan Ua Raġaille</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date when="1692">1692</date>
        <source>https://archive.org/details/dntaaoaginuraail03orah/page/n73/mode/1up</source>
      </publicationStmt>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div0 type="groupofpoems" >
        <div1 lang="en" type="poetry">
          <lg>
            <l>Woeful and bitter to me are the wounds of the land of Fodla,</l>
            <l>Who is sorely under a cloud whilst her Kinsfolk are heartsick;</l>
            <l>The trees that were strongest in affordine them shelter</l>
            <l>Have their branches lopped off and their roots withering in decay.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Long though thou hast been, O majestic, gentle-mannered Erin,</l>
            <l>A fair nursing-mother with hospitality and true knowledge;</l>
            <l>Henceforth shalt thou be an unwilling handmaid to every withered band,</l>
            <l>While every foreign boor shall have sucked thy breasts.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>And to crown my sorrow, behold it is a fit subject for tears,</l>
            <l>That every King of the dynasties who divide Europe amongst them</l>
            <l>Possesses his own fair, gentle spouse in prosperity and peace,</l>
            <l>While Banba is in pain without a consort, wedded though she be.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>We have lost the root-stock of Niall and the seed of Eoghan,</l>
            <l>And the bold champions, the warriors of the kingdom of Boruṁa;</l>
            <l>Of the hospitable race of Carthach, woe is me! we have not many alive,</l>
            <l>Nor of the chieftains of the Gael who were of renowned feats in battle.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>In sooth it is every violence of injustice on our part,</l>
            <l>Deceit and falsehood and treachery and dishonesty,</l>
            <l>Our want of union, and, instead, the tearing of each other’s throats,</l>
            <l>That have drawn down on Erin keenly the rage of the Mighty King.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Since we have lost Erin, and because of the extent of our misfortunes,</l>
            <l>And because of the overthrow of the nimble, strong warriors, who were not wanting in vigour,</l>
            <l>We entreat the noble Son of God and the Might of the Trinity,</l>
            <l>That those of them who are alive with us may thrive after them.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>The Gaels have lost their gentle, comely qualities;</l>
            <l>Charity, hospitality, manners, and sweet music;</l>
            <l>Wicked, alien boars it was that forced us under great oppression;</l>
            <l>I beseech the Only Son of God to grant relief to the Gaels.</l>
          </lg>
        </div1>
        <div1 lang="ga" type="poetry">
          <lg>
            <l>Is atuirseaċ gear liom créaċta críċ Fódla</l>
            <l>Fá sgamall go daor ‘sa gaolta clí-ḃreóiġte;</l>
            <l>Na cranna baḋ ṫréine ag déanaṁ dín dóiḃ sin</l>
            <l>Do gearraḋ a ngéaga ‘r a bpréaṁa crín-feoiġte.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Cé fada ḋuit, 'Éire, ṁaorḋa, ṁín-nósṁar,</l>
            <l>Ad’ ḃanaltrain tséiṁ le féile is fíor-eólus,</l>
            <l>Beir feasda ad’ ṁéirdrig fé gaċ críon-ċóisir,</l>
            <l>‘S gaċ ladrann coṁaiṫeaċ b’éis do ċlí ḋeóltaḋ.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Is mar ḃarra air mo ṁéala, feuċ gur díol deóra,</l>
            <l>Go ngaḃann gaċ récs don réim sin Roinn Eoruip</l>
            <l>A ḃairrḟionn tais féin go saoġalta síṫeóilte,</l>
            <l>Aċt Banba a bpéin gan céile is í posta!</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Do Ċailleamar préim-ṡlioċt Néill is síol Eogain,</l>
            <l>Is na fearaċoin tréana, laoċra ríoġaċt Bóirṁe,</l>
            <l>Den Ċaraṫ-ḟuil ḟéil, mo léan, ní’l puinn béo aguinn!</l>
            <l>Ná ṁaiṫe na nGaeḋeal do b'éaċtaċ gníoṁ coṁraic.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Is dearḃ gurab é gaċ éigion íogcóra,</l>
            <l>Ganguid is éiṫeaċ, claon is díoṫ-ċóṁall,</l>
            <l>Gan ceangal le ċéile, aċt raobaḋ rínn-sgórnaċ,</l>
            <l>Do ṫarraing ar Éirinn fraoċ an Ríoġ ċoṁaċtaig.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Dó ċailleamar Éire is méad ár mío-ċoṁṫrom,</l>
            <l>Is treasgairt na laoċ mear, treun, nár ṁí-ṫreóraċ,</l>
            <l>Air Arad-Ṁac Dé ‘s air ṫreun na Tríonóide</l>
            <l>Go mairfiḋ bá n-éir an mead so ḋíoḃ beó aguinn.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg>
            <l>Ċailleadar Gaoḋail a dtréiṫe caoin córaċ,</l>
            <l>Carṫanaċt, féile, beusa, is bínn-ċeólta;</l>
            <l>Alla-tuirc claon do ṫraoċ sinn faoi ṁór-smaċt;</l>
            <l>Agallaim Aon-Ṁac Dé air Gaoiḋil d’fóirṫin.</l>
          </lg>
        </div1>
      </div0>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

