<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://uisneac.com</id>
    <title>Uisneaċ</title>
    <link href="https://uisneac.com" />
    <updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <category term="Irish Myth" />
    <category term="Religion" />
    <category term="Orphism" />
    <category term="Greek" />
    <category term="Anglo-Saxon" />
    <category term="Magic" />
    <category term="Astrology" />
    <category term="Medieval" />
    <category term="Christianity" />
    <category term="Poetry" />
    <category term="Hittite" />
    <category term="Old Irish" />
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/Two-Carolingian-Poems/</id>
        <title>Two Carolingian Poems by Hibernicus Exul</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/Two-Carolingian-Poems/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/hint.css/2.4.1/hint.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;carolingian.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An anonymous Irish poet calling himself Hibernicus Exul, or the Irish Exile, wrote a number of poems in Latin for his lord, Charlemagne, during the 8th century AD. Some (most?) of these poems are captured in a work called Poetae Latinae Aevi Carolini, &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/poetaelatiniaevi00dm/page/392/mode/2up&#34;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; by Ernst Dümmler in 1881, which prints them in Latin and which, as far as I can tell, have not yet been translated to English except for a handful published in Poetry of the Carolingian Renaissance by Peter Godman in 1981.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This poet is anonymous, and identified himself only with this pseudonym. Historians have tried, through mere conjecture, to identify him with the other Irish scholars known to have been in the Carolingian court, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungal&#34;&gt;Dungal&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dicuil&#34;&gt;Dicuil&lt;/a&gt;, who certainly qualify as educated Irishmen far from home. But nothing can be known for sure. These two poems specifically are panegyrics for Charlemagne, and offer a glimpse into the scholastic Christianity of the 8th century AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I follow the poem numberings presented by Dümmler, and only post two for some light reading during Christmas. I will translate more later for completeness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O deus omnipotens, convexae conditor arcis,&lt;br&gt;
Terrarum et maris et quae tantus continet orbis,&lt;br&gt;
Suscipe vota tuae plebis, dignare rogatus&lt;br&gt;
Caesaris eximii Karoli firmare salutem;&lt;br&gt;
Multiplices vitam protendens, rector, in annos,&lt;br&gt;
Imperio oceanum consignans ordine metam,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;This is a double accusative construction, where *oceanum* and *metam* are the accusatives. The verb is a form of *consignare*, meaning to mark something as something or to assign a role; therefore, *consignans oceanum metam* means to assign the Ocean as a boundary.&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Hostibus oppressis firmata pace perenni,&lt;br&gt;
Optime quod princeps sedatum rite gubernet,&lt;br&gt;
Permulcente sua divino munere&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;This word *munere* can mean either a gift or an office or employment. Sextus Pompeius Festus [explains](https://archive.org/details/deverborumsigni00fest/page/140/mode/2up) this double meaning thus: *Mūnus sīgnificat officium, cum dīcitur quis mūnere fungī. Item dōnum quod officiī causā datur.* “‘Mūnus’ means office, when someone is said to perform his office. Also ‘gift’, since it’s given because of the service.” I take it in this context to refer to the office.&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; dextra.&lt;br&gt;
Unus in aetherea altitonans qui praesidet aula;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;The phrase *in aethera aula* is one where the noun and adjective are both in the ablative case, yet the phrase as a whole shows location. This is caused by the *in*, which transforms the meaning of the ablative to a kind of locative case.&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Convenit et solum terris regnare sub illo,&lt;br&gt;
Qui merito cunctis praestans mortalibus esset.&lt;br&gt;
Discedant variae sectae, discedat et error&lt;br&gt;
Antiquus, quondam male suasus ab ore maligni.&lt;br&gt;
Sancta fides niteat comitantcr gressibus altis,&lt;br&gt;
Cum Karoli magni ut vastum perlustret et orbem,&lt;br&gt;
Imperio dictoque simul domitis virtute superbis.&lt;br&gt;
Ac post immensos captos ex hoste triumphos,&lt;br&gt;
Cum victore suo victrix letetur et ipsa,&lt;br&gt;
Post tanta in terris post tot sublimia facta,&lt;br&gt;
Pleno tum demum completo temporis aevo,&lt;br&gt;
Felici centenos cursu evectus in annos.&lt;br&gt;
Alma fides obviam, comitante cohorte sororum,&lt;br&gt;
Virtutum, veniens Karolum super astra levabit,&lt;br&gt;
Perpetuam tribuens Christo praesente coronam.&lt;br&gt;
Versibus incompis, summo sed mentis amore,&lt;br&gt;
Haec tibi conficiens, Caesar: dignare superne&lt;br&gt;
Munera, quaeso, tui devoti sumere servi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His ego litterulis domino deposco salutem&lt;br&gt;
Perpetuam Karoli servulus ipse sui.&lt;br&gt;
His te, praeclara Gundrada, saluto, puella,&lt;br&gt;
Quae ore nitens pulchro, pulchrior es merito.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;This line should be read as *puella pulchrior es* “you are a maiden more beautiful still”. *pulchrior* is a comparator, even though there is no second thing to compare to. The translation of *ore* as “head, face” is contrasted with the translation of *ore* as “mouth” in Line 14, but a counterexample can be seen in the listed Classical quotation on the [Wiktionary page](https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/os#Latin) for *os*: *Gorgonis os pulcherrimum*, in which we happen to see the word *pulcher* used again.&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Littera, festina dominae conferre salutem&lt;br&gt;
Gundradae egregiae moribus et facie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O almighty God, creator of the vaulted firmament,&lt;br&gt;
Of lands and the sea and all that such a vast orb contains,&lt;br&gt;
Receive the prayers of your people; deign, when entreated,&lt;br&gt;
To strengthen the welfare of the excellent Caesar Charles,&lt;br&gt;
Extending his life, Ruler, prolonging his years,&lt;br&gt;
Assigning, in right order, the ocean as boundary of his empire,&lt;br&gt;
With enemies subdued and perennial peace established,&lt;br&gt;
That the excellent prince may rightly govern what has been pacified,&lt;br&gt;
Appeasing it with his right hand through divine office.&lt;br&gt;
Thunderous One on high who presides over the ethereal court;&lt;br&gt;
It is fitting also for one alone to reign on earth under Him,&lt;br&gt;
Who by merit would surpass all mortal men.&lt;br&gt;
Let various sects depart, let ancient error depart,&lt;br&gt;
Once wickedly urged by the mouth of the malign one.&lt;br&gt;
May holy faith shine, accompanying lofty deeds,&lt;br&gt;
As it traverses the vast realm of Charles the Great,&lt;br&gt;
With the proud subdued at once by empire and command through valor.&lt;br&gt;
And after immense triumphs captured over the enemy,&lt;br&gt;
When Victory herself rejoices with her victor,&lt;br&gt;
After so many sublime deeds upon the earth,&lt;br&gt;
Then, at last, when the full span of time is completed,&lt;br&gt;
He will be exalted in the course of a hundred happy years.&lt;br&gt;
Nourishing faith goes forth, accompanied by a cohort of sister&lt;br&gt;
Virtues, coming to Charles, will raise him above the stars,&lt;br&gt;
Bestowing an everlasting crown on him, in Christ’s presence.&lt;br&gt;
With unpolished verses, but with the highest love in the mind,&lt;br&gt;
Composing these for you, Caesar, deign from on high&lt;br&gt;
To accept these gifts, I beg, from your devoted servant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these little letters to my lord I earnestly wish for&lt;br&gt;
The everlasting welfare of Charles, whose meager servant I am.&lt;br&gt;
With these I greet you, illustrious Gundrada, maiden,&lt;br&gt;
Whose fair radiant countenance makes you the more beautiful.&lt;br&gt;
O Letters, hasten to my Lady, convey my well-wishes&lt;br&gt;
To Gundrada, eminent in character and mien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;3&#34;&gt;3.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VERSUS KAROLI IMPERATORIS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haec est vera fides, caeli quae ducit ad aulam,&lt;br&gt;
Hanc teneat, requiem quisquis habere cupit.&lt;br&gt;
Est etenim virtus cunctis credentibus ampla&lt;br&gt;
More fide trino phise placere deo.&lt;br&gt;
Summus apex Karolus Caesar, pax orbis optima,&lt;br&gt;
Huic turmas hominum subdere colla docet.&lt;br&gt;
Altior ut cuncti regni rex unus honore,&lt;br&gt;
More, fide, forma Caesar, ut opto prior,&lt;br&gt;
Qui sibi praesentis regni concesserat arcem,&lt;br&gt;
Arce poli summum det sibi, posco, locum.&lt;br&gt;
Exiguus regi paruum nunc reddo libellum&lt;br&gt;
Collectum ex variis flore comante rosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VERSES ON THE EMPEROR CHARLES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is true faith, which leads to the court of Heaven,&lt;br&gt;
Whosoever desires rest, let him hold to this.&lt;br&gt;
It is indeed a virtue, ample for all who believe,&lt;br&gt;
Who have faith in the threefold nature, which pleases God.&lt;br&gt;
The highest summit, Charles Caesar, best peace of the world,&lt;br&gt;
Instructs troops of men to bend their necks to him.&lt;br&gt;
That of all the kingdom the king may be highest,&lt;br&gt;
In manner, faith, and form like Caesar, as I wish him foremost,&lt;br&gt;
He who claimed for himself the stronghold of this present kingdom,&lt;br&gt;
May he likewise, I pray, earn the highest place, the stronghold of Heaven.&lt;br&gt;
Meek, I now render to the king this little book,&lt;br&gt;
Collected from various flowering roses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;Notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Poem-1&#34;&gt;Poem 1.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;footnotelist&#34;&gt;&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style: none; padding-left: 0; margin-left: 40px&#34;&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;1.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;This is a double accusative construction, where &lt;em&gt;oceanum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;metam&lt;/em&gt; are the accusatives. The verb is a form of &lt;em&gt;consignare&lt;/em&gt;, meaning to mark something as something or to assign a role; therefore, &lt;em&gt;consignans oceanum metam&lt;/em&gt; means to assign the Ocean as a boundary.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;2.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;This word &lt;em&gt;munere&lt;/em&gt; can mean either a gift or an office or employment. Sextus Pompeius Festus &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/deverborumsigni00fest/page/140/mode/2up&#34;&gt;explains&lt;/a&gt; this double meaning thus: &lt;em&gt;Mūnus sīgnificat officium, cum dīcitur quis mūnere fungī. Item dōnum quod officiī causā datur.&lt;/em&gt; “‘Mūnus’ means office, when someone is said to perform his office. Also ‘gift’, since it’s given because of the service.” I take it in this context to refer to the office.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;3.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;The phrase &lt;em&gt;in aethera aula&lt;/em&gt; is one where the noun and adjective are both in the ablative case, yet the phrase as a whole shows location. This is caused by the &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt;, which transforms the meaning of the ablative to a kind of locative case.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;4.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;This line should be read as &lt;em&gt;puella pulchrior es&lt;/em&gt; “you are a maiden more beautiful still”. &lt;em&gt;pulchrior&lt;/em&gt; is a comparator, even though there is no second thing to compare to. The translation of &lt;em&gt;ore&lt;/em&gt; as “head, face” is contrasted with the translation of &lt;em&gt;ore&lt;/em&gt; as “mouth” in Line 14, but a counterexample can be seen in the listed Classical quotation on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/os#Latin&#34;&gt;Wiktionary page&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;em&gt;os&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Gorgonis os pulcherrimum&lt;/em&gt;, in which we happen to see the word &lt;em&gt;pulcher&lt;/em&gt; used again.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
        <category term="Medieval" />
        <category term="Christianity" />
        <category term="Poetry" />
        <updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/The-Song-of-Lugh/</id>
        <title>The Song of Lugh</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/The-Song-of-Lugh/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;style&gt;
article .content img.same-size { width: 150px; height: 150px; object-fit: fill; margin: 15px 0 0 0; }
article .content img.wide-image { width: 100%; height: auto; object-fit: fill; margin: 15px 0 0 0; }
article .content img.half-image { width: 50%; height: auto; object-fit: fill; margin: 15px 0 0 0; }
article .content img.free-image { width: auto; height: auto; max-width: 100%; max-height: none; margin: 15px 0 0 0; }
img { align-self: center; }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/The-Song-of-Lugh/TuathaDeDanann.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On page 98 of &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/revueceltique12pari/page/n5/mode/2up&#34;&gt;Revue Celtique Vol. XII&lt;/a&gt;, Whitley Stokes’ translation of the &lt;em&gt;Cath Maige Tuired&lt;/em&gt; cuts off, leaving a speech given by Lugh to the &lt;em&gt;Tuatha Dé Danann&lt;/em&gt; untranslated due to the difficulty of the language. As far as I can tell, there are three authors who have tried to tackle this passage, being &lt;a href=&#34;https://storyarchaeology.com/about_us/&#34;&gt;Isolde Carmody&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;https://storyarchaeology.com/lug-taunts-the-enemy/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, as well as Bernard Mees in his &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/celtic-curses/1C98E6A5F9E316AC729361BC9D245890&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Celtic Curses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and one by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55859901-cath-maige-tuired&#34;&gt;Morgan Daimler&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;they/them&lt;/em&gt;), though Daimler calls herself ‘not a professional translator… a self-taught amateur’ in the book’s foreword. Carmody’s translation is, in my view, also amateurish, and Mees’ is only partial, leaving out a difficult portion in the middle; Daimler’s is somewhat better than Carmody’s but still falls into too many traps. So in the interest of the freedom of all knowledge, I will translate it myself, open to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manuscript, MS 5280 in the Harleian collection, was written in the 16th century by Giolla Riabhach Ó Cleirigh, a member of the famous Ó Cléirigh family of scribes and intellecutals (&lt;em&gt;Cléirigh&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;cléirech&lt;/em&gt; is ultimately from Latin &lt;em&gt;clericus&lt;/em&gt; or clerk). The &lt;em&gt;Cath&lt;/em&gt; story from folio 63r-69v was transcribed by Stokes, but he neglected the “Song of Lugh” which I am interested in here. Rudolf Thurneysen, thankfully, finished the transcription in &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/zeitschriftfrc12meyeuoft/page/402/mode/2up&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift fur Celtische Philologie&lt;/em&gt; Vol. XII pg. 403&lt;/a&gt;, along with the other portions of the Harleian 5280 which Stokes left untranslated, but did not offer a translation of his own. This transcription was apparently used by Elizabeth Gray in her 1982 translation of the &lt;em&gt;Cath&lt;/em&gt;, though she too left this song untranslated. There are many words which are abbreviated by a ‘macron’ (see &lt;a href=&#34;#Abbreviations&#34;&gt;below&lt;/a&gt;) which leaves ambiguity at many parts of the text and which make translation of an already-ambiguous poetic text extremely difficult. But modern dictionaries and the online availability of pretty much all Old Irish texts as references give a modern translator an equal advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lugh chants this chant before the assembled army of the &lt;em&gt;Tuatha Dé Danann&lt;/em&gt; standing before the Fomorian troops, of which it is said “to attack the Fomorian host on that day was ‘striking a head against a cliff,’ was ‘a hand in a serpent’s nest,’ was ‘a face up to lire.’” He stands on one leg, with one arm, and one eye while circling the &lt;em&gt;Tuatha Dé&lt;/em&gt;, demonstrating an instance of &lt;em&gt;corrguinecht&lt;/em&gt;, the Old Irish magical stance often paired with &lt;em&gt;glám dícenn&lt;/em&gt;, magical poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This endeavor must, then, begin from first principles with a transcription of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://iiif.bl.uk/uv/#?manifest=https://bl.digirati.io/iiif/ark:/81055/vdc_100123802477.0x000001&#34;&gt;manuscript&lt;/a&gt;, which I will give here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;The-Scribe’s-Hand&#34;&gt;The Scribe’s Hand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must begin transcription by analyzing the scribe’s handwriting, including the common letters and abbreviations, ligatures, and lenitions. Note that the Old, Middle, and Modern Irish alphabets do not share all of the English alphabet’s letters, such as J, K, W, or X, which are absent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;English Letter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Scribe’s Letter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;English Letter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Scribe’s Letter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;A.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;L&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;L.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;B.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;M&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;M.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;C.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;N.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;D.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;O&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;O.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;E&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;E.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;P&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;P.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;F&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;F.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;R&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;R.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;G&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;G.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;S&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;S.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;H&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;H.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;T&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;T.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;I.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;U&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;U.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Ligatures&#34;&gt;Ligatures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most letters follow a consistent script, a form of insular script, but a close reader may notice some aberrant symbols. The scribe, to save space, will often combine two letters into one glyph in a process called “ligature”. A table of some of these occurrences is presented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;English Letters&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Scribe’s Glyph&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;English Letters&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Scribe’s Glyph&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A+R&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;AR.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;E+T&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ET2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;B+R&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;BR.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;I+R&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;IR.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D+E&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;DE.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;O+R&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;OR.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D+O&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;DO.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;S+I&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;SI.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;E+C&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;EC.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D+E&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;DE.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;E+I&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;EI.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D+E+A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;DEA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;E+N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;EN.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D+E+G&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;DEG.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;E+R&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ER.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;D+E+N&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;DEN.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See how in D ligatures, the D glyph, which usually has a nearly-horizontal leftward stroke on top, is rotated so that it’s top stroke points upwards, making it appear more similar to an A. Also note how in R ligatures, the downstroke that forms the spine of the R glyph can be completely omitted, and only the arm of the glyph left remaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be said that such a stroke only represents an R if the lower portion moves to the right as it does in a regular R character: moving to the left means something utterly different. See this abbreviation which uses a similar falling arm, but which has a bottom stroke curving leftward, looking similar to a modern semicolon (;) or a &lt;a href=&#34;https://guides.loc.gov/manuscript-facsimiles/deciphering-scribal-abbreviations#s-lib-ctab-24229924-3&#34;&gt;yogh&lt;/a&gt; symbol (ȝ) of Old English. This word ultimately is “AMNUS”, meaning “cruel”, with the final arm representing the “-US”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;AMNUS.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;half-image&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 20px;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;R&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;R-Ligature&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;-US&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;R_FLOURISH.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;free-image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;R_LIGATURE.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;free-image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;US.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;free-image&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of ligature rests wholly on the scribe’s preference at the time of writing. For example, we can see him write the letters E+T either as ligature or separately at different locations on the folio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;ET Ligature&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;ET Standalone&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ET2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;ET.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;spacer&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Abbreviations&#34;&gt;Abbreviations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many words are shortened by means of abbreviation, and most of those by a &lt;em&gt;macron&lt;/em&gt; or bar above the letter. The reader is meant to understand that the word ending which has been abbreviated is so common, or so easily derived from context, that writing out the full word is not necessary. We can see at the top of the folio that the scribe abbreviates “&lt;em&gt;Tuatha Dé Danann&lt;/em&gt;” as “.t.d.d.”; it is understood that the reader, if he has been reading along, will naturally assume TDD stands for &lt;em&gt;Tuatha Dé Danann&lt;/em&gt; from context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;TDD.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most abbreviations, though, use a &lt;em&gt;macron&lt;/em&gt;. In this phrase below, we have only the letters “FER NER̄” to read from, but one who has been reading the entire story will recall that the conflict is between the &lt;em&gt;fer fomoire&lt;/em&gt; (men of the Fomorians) and the &lt;em&gt;fer nErenn&lt;/em&gt; (men of Ireland), so it is not necessary to finish writing the word &lt;em&gt;nErenn&lt;/em&gt;, one can simply assume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;FER NERENN.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;half-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, we also see the scribe abbreviate the phrase “&lt;em&gt;fine fomoire&lt;/em&gt;” on both words, leaving us with only “FĪE FOMR̄” to read (note: a &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt; is an Old Irish patrilineal kin-group).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;FINE FOMOIRE.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;half-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often common Irish words will be shortened due to the commonality or their use. See here the word “D’FHOGAIL”, meaning “for plundering / for defense”; we are meant to infer its common suffix “&lt;em&gt;-ail&lt;/em&gt;” based on grammar context:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;DFHOGAIL.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;half-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A word can be expressed entirely through ligature and abbreviation, such as this one which Stokes rendered as “DIDIU”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;DIDIU.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One must be an Old Irish scholar to correctly fill in these gaps with the appropriate words, which is why I resolve my uncertainties through Stokes’ methods used in previous sections of this text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Reading-Letters&#34;&gt;Reading Letters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reader should also note that in this script, a letter may consist on many strokes, but the initial stroke of a letter is designated by a wedge or triangular stroke (a serif): if a downward stroke does not have this serif, it is not a new letter. See how we can differentiate between the M and N in this word “FOMNAI”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;FOMNAI.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;free-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite there being five near-identical downward strokes in the middle of this word, the upper serifs differentiate letter-initial strokes from strokes that continue a letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;FOMNAI_CIRCLED.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;free-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one exception is the letter U, in which both downstrokes contain a serif. See here the word “LUG”, in which the L and U collectively have three wedges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LUG.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;half-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But sometimes the scribe writes too quickly and his U’s slide across the folio appearing like a different glyph. Here is the word “TUATH” with a speedily-written U and a lenited T marked with a dot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;TUATH.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;half-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also see an occasional capital letter, sometimes applied randomly to a letter in a word. There are larger capitals on the margins of the folio, and smaller capital letters inline with a sentence. These are typically easy to identify with their lower-case counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Capital&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;A_CAP.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Capital A - Marginal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;A_CAP_INLINE.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Capital A - Inline&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;R_CAP.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Capital R - Marginal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;D_CAP_INLINE.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Capital D - Inline&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the word below, the scribe writes an initial capital I, but then also a capital N after it, which could confuse a casual reader. Together this makes the common Old Irish word “intan” meaning “then / while”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;INtan.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;half-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also entirely unique symbols used to denote common syllables. The three glyphs below are rendered by Stokes as “CONSE…”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;UNKNOWN.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;half-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire “Song of Lugh” is preceded by this strange double stroke symbol which, as far as I can tell, corresponds to no letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;SYMBOL.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thurneysen uses this symbol to demarcate a kind of ‘overflow line’ for words that should appear elsewhere in the text. In his transcription he moves the words which come after this strange symbol (but are still on the same line) to after the line that begins “Arotroi cath comartan…”. Presumably the scribe wanted the ‘A’ in “Arotroi” to be larger and to sit on the margin, but didn’t want to waste precious vellum with empty space, so he finished out the previous line with text that was meant to go after the “Arotroi…” line. Therefore, Thurneysen moved the “silsit- …” line to after the “Arotroi…” line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of Stokes doing the same thing for this symbol on folio 67v. He moves the “ol Corpri…” line to after the “Os tusai…” line. The scribe then, again, wanted the first letter of this new paragraph to be larger in the margin. So in my transcription, the “silsit- …” line will also follow after the “Arotroi…” line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;SYMBOL_IN_USE.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;STOKES_TRANSCRIPTION.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Transcription&#34;&gt;Transcription&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The untranslated poem appears on the page as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;POEM.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will go line by line and merely relocate the letters from insular into Roman script. Note that a dash ‘-’ indicates a macron over the preceding letter, a double parenthesis ‘()’ indicates a curved stroke above the previous letter, and a plus ‘+’ indicates a downstroke with a crossbar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Arotroi cat comartan isin cath irgal robris comlondo f-slecht- slu-&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;silsit- riaslu- sioabrai iath fer fomnai cuife&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;cithai fir genrogain lentor gala fordomaisit fordomcloisid f-an&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;dechraiged fir duib becc find nomtain- fó fó fé fé cléamainsi no&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE5.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;efit- maim- iernelscoth- trietrenc-daib druag Nimcredbod catha f()c()cha&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE6.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;nesit- mede midege fornemairces f-luachoir loisces ma+tal- tshuides&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE7.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;ma+torain- trogais ni comairsid f()cechnaie go comair ogma sachu go&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE8.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;comair ne- agus talom go comair g()oa- agus esa+u. Drem madh mo dremsie duib&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE9.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Moslu-so slu- mor murnech mochtsailech bruithe nt-oirech rogeno+&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;LINE10.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;wide-image&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;et- dacri ataf-roi cath comortai. Arot&#39;&#39;i&lt;/i&gt; (Stokes&#39; translation resumes here)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Thurneysen’s-Transcription&#34;&gt;Thurneysen’s Transcription&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well before my undertaking of this work, Rudolf Thurneysen completed a transcription of this passage in &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/zeitschriftfrc12meyeuoft/page/402/mode/2up&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zeitschrift fur Celtische Philologie&lt;/em&gt; Vol. XII pg. 403&lt;/a&gt;, which I will provide now for comparison with my own. Note that a dash once again indicates a &lt;em&gt;macron&lt;/em&gt; above the preceding letter, and text in italics has been filled in by Thurneysen in the place of &lt;em&gt;macrons&lt;/em&gt; which are sufficiently obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atroroi cat comartan isincathirgal robris comlondo f&lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;slecht- slu- silsit- riaslu- sioa- brai iath fer fomnai . cuifecithai fir genrogain lentor gala. fordomaisit fordomcloisid f&lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;andechraiged fir duib becc find nomtam . fó fó fé fé clé amainsi noefit- mann iernelscoth- trietrenc&lt;em&gt;er&lt;/em&gt;daib druag. Nimcredbod catha fricricha nesit- mede midege fornemairces f&lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;luachoir loisces martal- tṡuides martorai&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;n trogais . incomairsid fricechnaie gocomair ogma sachu gocomair nem 7 talom gocomair grioan 7 esqu Drem níadh modremsie duib Moslu-so slu- mor murnech mochtsailech bruithe n&lt;em&gt;er&lt;/em&gt;toirech rogenoir et- dacri ataf&lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;roi cath comortai. arot&lt;em&gt;ra&lt;/em&gt;i.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may notice, like I did, two errors in this transcription, either due to Thurneysen or, more likely, his printer. The first word &lt;em&gt;Arotroi&lt;/em&gt; on the manuscript is here rendered “Atroroi”, meaning &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/4923&#34;&gt;“to fail”&lt;/a&gt;; and the word &lt;em&gt;nicomairsid&lt;/em&gt; is rendered as &lt;em&gt;incomairsid&lt;/em&gt;. The former error I attribute to the printer, because the &lt;em&gt;arotrai&lt;/em&gt; which ends the poem is printed correctly; the latter I attribute to Thurneysen, since the three downstrokes which make up both &lt;em&gt;in-&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ni-&lt;/em&gt; can be easily confused, and I am only more confident in my own interpretation because of high-quality digital imagery that isn’t obscured by light and shadow or by tired eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Word-Analysis&#34;&gt;Word Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The words are divided here based on how they appear to me to be separated on the folio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Ref.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Written&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Old Irish&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;P.o.S.&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;English&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 1.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Arotroi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/4913&#34;&gt;at-reig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Arise!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cath&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;battle&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comartan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10761&#34;&gt;comart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mutual-striking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;isin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Irish_grammar&#34;&gt;isin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;in, at or into&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cath&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cath&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;battle&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;irgal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/search?q=irgal&#34;&gt;airgal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen. pl.?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;boiling / upheaval / battle / strife&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;robris&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ro + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/6848&#34;&gt;brisid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;past.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;perfective-marker + break or overthrow, defeat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comlondo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/11408&#34;&gt;comlann&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10554&#34;&gt;com&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/30660&#34;&gt;lond&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nom. s.?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;contest, battle, fight or equally-fierce&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;f-slecht- (forslecht(aib?))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/23272&#34;&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37871&#34;&gt;slecht&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37939&#34;&gt;sligid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;dat. or 3rd. pass. s.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;upon, for + hewing, cutting, slaughtering? or lay low, slay, defeat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;slu- (slúaig)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37981&#34;&gt;slúag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;host, army&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 2.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;silsit- (silsiter)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37939&#34;&gt;sligid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd. pl. pass. fut.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;will lay low, will slay, will defeat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;riaslu- (riasluag)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/34869&#34;&gt;ria&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37981&#34;&gt;slúag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;dat.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;before + host, army&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;sioabrai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37365&#34;&gt;síabraid&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37359&#34;&gt;síabair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj. or part.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bewitched, aroused to fury, or relating to phantoms&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;iath&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/27115&#34;&gt;íath&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen. pl.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;of the lands / territories&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/21665&#34;&gt;fer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen. pl.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;of the men&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fomnai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/23219&#34;&gt;fo-moinethar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wary, vigilant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cuife&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/13490&#34;&gt;cuife&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cave, den (of animals)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 3.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cithai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/9254&#34;&gt;cit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen. pl.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;sheep&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fir&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/21665&#34;&gt;fer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen. pl.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;men&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;genrogain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/8581&#34;&gt;cen&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/35441&#34;&gt;rogain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;without + choice&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;lentor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/29895&#34;&gt;lenaid&lt;/a&gt; (lend + ar or lentar)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd. s. or 3rd. pass.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;stay attach to, cling to&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gala&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/25277&#34;&gt;gal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen. s.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;heat, mist or war fury, valor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;for&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/23272&#34;&gt;for&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;upon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;domaisit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/18065&#34;&gt;do-maisi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;elaborates, devises, invents, concocts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;for&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/23272&#34;&gt;for&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;upon, on&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;domcloisid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;dom + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/9588&#34;&gt;cloisid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;to me + listen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;f-an (foran)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fora + n-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;upon, on + (relative marker)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 4.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;dechraiged&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/14925&#34;&gt;dechraigidir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd s. pret. subj.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mark out, distinguish (intrans.) / scatter, stand apart, differ (trans.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fir&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/21665&#34;&gt;fer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nom. pl. or gen. s.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;men or of a man&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;duib&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/18985&#34;&gt;dub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;black, dark&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;becc&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/5512&#34;&gt;becc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;small, little / few&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;find&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/22134&#34;&gt;finn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bright, white&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nomtain- (nomtainn)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33244&#34;&gt;noem&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/39627&#34;&gt;táin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;holy, sacred + raid, driving-off&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fó&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/22335&#34;&gt;fo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joy!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fó&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/22335&#34;&gt;fo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Joy!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fé&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/21372&#34;&gt;fé&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;woe!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;37&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fé&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/21372&#34;&gt;fé&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;woe!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;38&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cleamainsi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/9397&#34;&gt;clé&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/3125&#34;&gt;amein&lt;/a&gt; + si&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;evil! + thusly / so! + emph.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;no&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 5.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;efit-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33244&#34;&gt;noíb&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/34382&#34;&gt;pít&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;holy, sacred + food, ration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;41&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;maim- (máime?)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/31501&#34;&gt;mám&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fistful&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;iernelscoth-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/27226&#34;&gt;ier&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33060&#34;&gt;nel&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/36595&#34;&gt;scothach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;across, beyond + cloud + fluffy, tufted&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;trietrenc-daib&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/41608&#34;&gt;tre&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/41798&#34;&gt;tren&lt;/a&gt; + cerdaib&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;through + strong + arts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;druag&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/18853&#34;&gt;druí&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen. s.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;druid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nimcredbod&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ni + me + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/12821&#34;&gt;credbaid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;does not + me + shrink, consume, gnaw&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;catha&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/8344&#34;&gt;cath&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gen.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;of battle&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;47&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;f()c()cha (fricricha)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/24329&#34;&gt;fri&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/12912&#34;&gt;crich&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;acc.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;against, towards + land, territory&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 6.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;48&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nesit-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33134&#34;&gt;nesaigid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;past pass.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;were wounded&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mede&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/31852&#34;&gt;méit&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/31755&#34;&gt;meide&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/31721&#34;&gt;med&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;size, greatness or nape, corpse or match, equal opponent&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;midege&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32160&#34;&gt;midach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;pl.?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;champion, hero / valiant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;51&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fornemairces&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;for + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33070&#34;&gt;nem&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/1779&#34;&gt;aircisid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd s. pres. ind.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;on/upon + heaven + meet/encounter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;52&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;f-luachoir&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;for + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/30761&#34;&gt;lúachair&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/30762&#34;&gt;lúachair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;on/upon + rushes (i.e. the plant) or brightness, brilliance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;53&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;loisces&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/30563&#34;&gt;loiscid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd. s. pres. ind.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;burns&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;54&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ma+tal- (martal)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/27721&#34;&gt;mar&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/39932&#34;&gt;talam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;as + the earth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;55&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;tshuides&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/35940&#34;&gt;suidid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd s. pres. ind.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;sits&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 7.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ma+torain- (martorainn)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/27721&#34;&gt;mar&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/41429&#34;&gt;torann&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;as + thunder, battle din&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;trogais&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/41996&#34;&gt;trogaid&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/41998&#34;&gt;trogain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd s. pres. ind.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gives birth, brings forth or sunrise, daybreak (metaph. “sun-birth”)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ni&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33147&#34;&gt;ni&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;not&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;59&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comairsid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10641&#34;&gt;comaircid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;inquires, asks / cries out&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;f()cechnaie (fricechnaie)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/24329&#34;&gt;fri&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/7528&#34;&gt;cech&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33235&#34;&gt;naie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;to + every + one&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;61&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;go&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comair&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10630&#34;&gt;comair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;in front of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;63&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ogma&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33573&#34;&gt;Ogma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ogma&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;64&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;sachu&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/38252&#34;&gt;sochonn&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;wise?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;go&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 8.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;66&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comair&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10630&#34;&gt;comair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;in front of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ne-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33070&#34;&gt;nem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;heaven&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;68&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;agus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;69&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;talom&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/39932&#34;&gt;talam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nom. S.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;earth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;go&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;71&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comair&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10630&#34;&gt;comair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;in front of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;g()oa- (grioan)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/26628&#34;&gt;grían&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;dat.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;the sun&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;73&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;agus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;conj.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;and&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;74&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;esa+u&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/20410&#34;&gt;ésca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;dat.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;moon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Drem&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/18631&#34;&gt;dremm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nom.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;band, company&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;76&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;niadh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33151&#34;&gt;nia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;pl. gen.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;warrior, champion&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;77&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32400&#34;&gt;mo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;pro.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;my&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;78&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;dreimsie&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/18631&#34;&gt;dremm&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/38191&#34;&gt;so&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Noun&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;band, company + this / emphatic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;79&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;duib&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/18985&#34;&gt;dub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;black, dark or massive, great&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 9.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;80&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Moslu-so&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32400&#34;&gt;mo&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37981&#34;&gt;slúag&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/38191&#34;&gt;so&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;my + army + this, here / emphatic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;81&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;slu-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37981&#34;&gt;slúag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nom.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;host, army, war assembly&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;82&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32548&#34;&gt;mor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;great, big&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;murnech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32798&#34;&gt;muirnech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;adj&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;spirited, tumultuous, rowdy, joyous&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;84&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mochtsailech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32411&#34;&gt;moch&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32422&#34;&gt;mochta&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/35988&#34;&gt;saílech&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/35989&#34;&gt;saílechtu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;early, speedy or great, mighty + thoughtful, hopeful or hope&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;85&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bruithe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/7139&#34;&gt;bruithe&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/7090&#34;&gt;bruid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;past part.?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;boiling, melting&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;86&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nt-oirech (nertoirech)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33116&#34;&gt;nert&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/1895&#34;&gt;airech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;pl.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;strength + nobles, lords&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;87&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rogeno+ (rogenoir)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/25186&#34;&gt;gainithir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;pret. 3rd? s? intrans.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is/are born&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Line 10.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;88&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;et- (etir)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/20789&#34;&gt;etir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;between&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;89&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;dacri&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/14080&#34;&gt;da&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/12895&#34;&gt;crí&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;two + shapes, forms, bodies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ataf-roi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/4927&#34;&gt;attá&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/22676&#34;&gt;fo-fich&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3rd. s. perf. pres. subj.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;would, could attack&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;91&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cath&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cath&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;battle, war&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comortai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10761&#34;&gt;comart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mutual-striking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;93&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Arot’&#39;i (Arotroi)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/4913&#34;&gt;at-reig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;imp.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Arise!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Notes-on-Words&#34;&gt;Notes on Words&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. “Arotroi” is hard to place, nothing like it appears in eDIL. Thankfully, we need not guess, since on &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/eriu_1916_8/page/173/mode/1up&#34;&gt;pg. 173 of Ériu 8&lt;/a&gt;, within a transcription of the &lt;em&gt;Cath Airtig&lt;/em&gt; from the Book of Lecan, we see a scribal note that reads &lt;em&gt;Arotroi (.i. eirig)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/4913&#34;&gt;Eirig (At-reig)&lt;/a&gt; is established to mean “rise up”, or here, “Arise!”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. eDIL lists this word as a verbal noun of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/12254&#34;&gt;con-oirg&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “mutual striking” or “striking together”, implying that the battle in question here is one of two armies striking together in mutual slaughter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/25277&#34;&gt;gal&lt;/a&gt; is listed as “heat, mental hotness”, and &lt;em&gt;irgal&lt;/em&gt; is listed as a compound with &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/21985&#34;&gt;fichid&lt;/a&gt; to mean “battle heat, fury”, and &lt;em&gt;cathirgal&lt;/em&gt; appears under &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/8344&#34;&gt;cath&lt;/a&gt; meaning “battle-fury”. &lt;em&gt;irgal&lt;/em&gt; appears in the entry for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/17143&#34;&gt;do-airissedar&lt;/a&gt;, where &lt;em&gt;tarrassaid inn irgal&lt;/em&gt; is translated as “the conflict paused”. Here we can take &lt;em&gt;cathirgal&lt;/em&gt; to be one word, since there is no spacing between letters in the manuscript, and the meaning then becomes something like “the battle-fury broke”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7. This word usually means “breaks, smashes” according to eDIL, but when combined with &lt;em&gt;cath&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;irgal&lt;/em&gt;, etc, which it is here, then means “overthrows, defeats, routs”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8. In the same way as &lt;em&gt;comlann&lt;/em&gt; is given as &lt;em&gt;com&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;lán&lt;/em&gt;, “equally + full”, I take this word as &lt;em&gt;com&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;lond&lt;/em&gt;, “equally + fierce, angry”. Mees renders this word as “with fury”, which I essentially agree with. The word-final ‘o’ can be an adjectival suffix. In trying to figure out this sentence, I also take this adjective &lt;em&gt;comlondo&lt;/em&gt; to be attached to the verb &lt;em&gt;robris&lt;/em&gt;, acting as an adverbial modifier giving a meaning of “breaks fiercely” or “overthrows furiously”, which again essentially agrees with Mees’ translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9. The first part is obviously &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt;. The second part could be &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37871&#34;&gt;slecht&lt;/a&gt;, a noun, meaning a division or the act of hewing, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37939&#34;&gt;sligid&lt;/a&gt;, a verb, meaning similarly to cut, hew, or throw down (i.e. an army). Both words, and both constructions (i.e. noun or verb) essentially describe the army in question as one that hews habitually, so we can give the English translation of “hewing host” or “over-slaughtering army”, once again in agreement with Mees’ translation. The word-final macron can be assumed as a conjugational ending or declension, and likely monosyllabic, probably &lt;em&gt;slechta&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;slechtaib&lt;/em&gt;. It can go either way, but I take this word to be the verbal noun of &lt;em&gt;sligid&lt;/em&gt;, giving us “upon/on the hewing hosts”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10. Following the discussion in Note 9, I take &lt;em&gt;slu-&lt;/em&gt; here to be &lt;em&gt;slúaig&lt;/em&gt;, that is “slúag” in the genitive, since for the noun “forslecht” to describe the &lt;em&gt;slúag&lt;/em&gt; we must have &lt;em&gt;forslecht slúaig&lt;/em&gt; “the hewing of the host”, or perhaps it is merely &lt;em&gt;forslecht slúag&lt;/em&gt; “the hewing of the hosts”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13. This word is derived either from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37365&#34;&gt;síabraid&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/37359&#34;&gt;síabair&lt;/a&gt;, with the latter pertaining to supernatural beings, phantoms, specters, etc. according to eDIL, and which agrees with Mees’ and Carmody’s translations of this word as “phantom”, and with the former meaning “enchanted, aroused, whipped into a fury, even to a supernatural fury”. I take the former derivation to be superior on the grounds of meaning, since there is no indication of a “phantom host” otherwise, but Lugh is engaging in the act of bewitching and arousing his army through incantation, so this is the army before which is the destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17. See also this word referenced in &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/14268&#34;&gt;daire&lt;/a&gt;, taken to mean an animal den or thicket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;18. The combination of &lt;em&gt;cuife&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cithai&lt;/em&gt; makes no sense. The words may even be one word that is split in half by a line break. Mees reads this as &lt;em&gt;cuifecithai&lt;/em&gt; “comes together”, and Carmody as “set aside”. Mees’ translation is a reasonable one—he renders it as a form of &lt;em&gt;com&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;fichid&lt;/em&gt;, and we see in eDIL under the entry for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10554&#34;&gt;com&lt;/a&gt;: “Before f (earlier *w) co (cóir), later cob cub (cobair, cobodail, cubaid, cubus, cobfolaid, cobfuil).” With an established -b form of &lt;em&gt;com&lt;/em&gt;, he adds &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/21985&#34;&gt;fichid&lt;/a&gt; which takes on some conjugation, perhaps a form of the preterite singular &lt;em&gt;fechtae&lt;/em&gt; “he fought” or passive present plural &lt;em&gt;fichitir&lt;/em&gt; “they (pass.) fight”. We can imagine that there is some dialect variance at play, or that the scribe was copying words he didn’t understand the meaning of (pure conjecture of course). I propose that this word is a compound noun of &lt;em&gt;cuife&lt;/em&gt;, “cave, den”, and “cit”, “sheep”, the latter of which is a form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/8919&#34;&gt;cethnat&lt;/a&gt; as listed on eDIL, or of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/9260&#34;&gt;cith&lt;/a&gt; which is identified with &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/13507&#34;&gt;cuilén&lt;/a&gt;, “pup, cub”. In any case, giving a meaning of “a den of young pups / sheep”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;21. This word is either &lt;em&gt;lentar&lt;/em&gt;, as listed in eDIL for the present passive singular, or a compound of &lt;em&gt;lent&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;lend&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;ar&lt;/em&gt;, a 3rd person present active, with a meaning of “stays attached to, clings to”. eDIL gives an example of the latter as “co rralsat sis anchoram; ro lend ar bendchopor in derthaige”, giving us a perfect example of &lt;em&gt;lent ar&lt;/em&gt; elsewhere. &lt;em&gt;lentar&lt;/em&gt; is used more flexibly as a regular passive verb. Along with the next word, &lt;em&gt;gala&lt;/em&gt;, we have a meaning of “adhering/one adheres to valor” or “staying/one stays attached to warlike fury”, etc, and a broader meaning of &lt;em&gt;cuife cithai fir gen rogain lentor gala&lt;/em&gt;, “a den of sheep are men without wills which adhere to war-fury”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;24. This word is seldom attested, and was only identified 20 years ago by Liam Bretnach, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/domaisi#Old_Irish&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but nonetheless fits perfectly. This would then be an elsewhere-unattested 3rd person plural active indicative form. We could take a meaning of “over-cunning” or “over-scheming”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;27. See the note in eDIL for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/23272&#34;&gt;for&lt;/a&gt;, which explains the use of &lt;em&gt;fora&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;n-&lt;/em&gt; in a relative clause which allows for the word to take the form of &lt;em&gt;fora&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;28. In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/14925&#34;&gt;eDIL listing&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;em&gt;dechraigidir&lt;/em&gt;, we see an identical form in &lt;em&gt;fria ndechraiged&lt;/em&gt;, a preterite subjunctive 3rd person singular. So it is tempting to break with pattern and interpret the macron over the ‘f’ which begins this word as &lt;em&gt;friandechraiged&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;forandechraiged&lt;/em&gt;, but I find it more likely that this word continues the series of &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; words. The word should be taken as &lt;em&gt;fora n-dechraiged&lt;/em&gt;. As for meaning, this would indicate that the ‘fir’ subsequently mentioned distinguish themselves; we can translate this as “greatly distinguished”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;30. &lt;em&gt;duib&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;dub&lt;/em&gt; has the meaning of “black”, but also of “great, mighty” or “dire,” and is used later interchangeably or with &lt;em&gt;mór&lt;/em&gt;. However here I will take it to mean “black” or “dark”. Mees and Daimler use this word when it appears later to mean “to you”, with the modern Irish meaning of &lt;em&gt;daoibh&lt;/em&gt;, but I find a form of &lt;em&gt;dub&lt;/em&gt; “black” to be far more likely on grounds of grammar and meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;33. An alternate reading is &lt;em&gt;nomtam-&lt;/em&gt;, an ambiguity which Thurneysen notes, but I view &lt;em&gt;nomtain-&lt;/em&gt; as the far more likely reading due to the subtle serif on the middle downstroke of the supposed ‘-m’, indicating that this is actually an &lt;em&gt;-in&lt;/em&gt;. This also allows us to accurately evaluate the macron over the ‘n’, as being a common double ‘n’ ending, whereas an ‘m’ ending leaves us with no clear option for the macron. I would like for this word to be a form of something like &lt;em&gt;nomtaid&lt;/em&gt;, but there is no such word in any dictionary, so I must interpret this as a compound of &lt;em&gt;noíb&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;táinn&lt;/em&gt;, with a meaning of “sacred, holy + raid, driving-off”, essentially describing what the Tuatha Dé intends to enact upon the Fomorians. The word then is a verb meaning “drives off, raids”. eDIL attests that in Middle Irish the former word is more often written as &lt;em&gt;noem&lt;/em&gt;, or similar forms, over &lt;em&gt;noíb&lt;/em&gt;. The latter word is well known, but does not appear listed with a double &lt;em&gt;-nn&lt;/em&gt; ending; this may be a scribal variation, but may also indicate that the second word is truly a form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/40004&#34;&gt;tain&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “time, while, occurrence”. This meaning is linguistically safer, however on grounds of meaning alone I find this alternative less likely, since “sacred time, holy time” would seemingly be disconnected from any established meaning in this line. However, I am ultimately not very confident in this translation because of the unaccounted-for &lt;em&gt;-nn&lt;/em&gt; ending and the leap required to make this a verb. It is also possible that the initial word &lt;em&gt;noem&lt;/em&gt; is the final afjective in the list and not connected to &lt;em&gt;tainn&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;34. This word has a more literal meaning of “good”, but I translate it as “joy”, to better contrast with the following “woe!” It may be simply a feature of English that woe is thing that is felt, so to keep the pairing consistent, &lt;em&gt;fo .i. maith&lt;/em&gt; must likewise become a “goodness that is felt” i.e. joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;40. &lt;em&gt;no efit-&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;noefit-&lt;/em&gt; as Thurneysen gives it, is perhaps the most difficult word in this text. Nothing even close to it appears in eDIL or any other common dictionary. So the following explanation will be only tentative at best. However, I suspect this is a compound of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33244&#34;&gt;noíb&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/34382&#34;&gt;pít&lt;/a&gt;; the first element means “holy, sacred”, and is also in my explanation of &lt;em&gt;nomtainn&lt;/em&gt; in Note 33, the latter is &lt;em&gt;-fit&lt;/em&gt;, a later version of the word &lt;em&gt;pít&lt;/em&gt;, meaning a food or ration. This latter element is shown to be used in compound words as the secondary element, such as &lt;em&gt;doborfiit&lt;/em&gt;, “water-diet” (i.e. a monk’s fasting), or &lt;em&gt;tercphit&lt;/em&gt;, “meager-rations”, and is identified with the Old Irish word &lt;em&gt;proind&lt;/em&gt; as well as the Latin &lt;em&gt;uita&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;vita&lt;/em&gt;, meaning the food that sustains one’s life. The initial element &lt;em&gt;noe&lt;/em&gt; is a form of &lt;em&gt;noíb&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;noem&lt;/em&gt;, but then we must explain why in &lt;em&gt;nomtainn&lt;/em&gt; this word appears with an ‘m’ and in this word without a final ‘m’: this is caused by lenition of the final ‘m’ between two slender vowels with the latter word’s ‘f’ preserved (phonologically the lenited ‘m’ -&amp;gt; ‘v’ may sound identical to an ‘f’). We see the word &lt;em&gt;noem&lt;/em&gt; with a lenited ‘m’ in many compounds in the eDIL entry: &lt;em&gt;naem&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;fót&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;naomhfód&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;naem&lt;/em&gt;+ &lt;em&gt;port&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;naomhport&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;noem&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;erlam&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;naomhērlamh&lt;/em&gt;. The ‘m’ in &lt;em&gt;nomtainn&lt;/em&gt; remains because of two surrounding broad vowels, which is seen also in eDIL, e.g. &lt;em&gt;noemcorp&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, accounting for the macron, we have &lt;em&gt;noefita&lt;/em&gt; meaning “holy food” or “divine sustenance”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;41. This word is truly hard to read. The manuscript shows four downstrokes for the final letter(s), which could be, most likely, either an “-im” or an “-nn”. To me there seems to be a slightly larger serif on the second downstroke, implying an “-im” ending and giving this word as “maim-”, with a macron still to be accounted for. The word is ultimately thus a form of the word &lt;em&gt;mám&lt;/em&gt; such as &lt;em&gt;máime&lt;/em&gt; (gen. s.). A genitive form is given in eDIL to show a unit of measure, e.g. &lt;em&gt;lán máime&lt;/em&gt; “full of a fist” or “a fist full”, and we could have a unit of measurement for the supposed &lt;em&gt;fit&lt;/em&gt; “food” in the previous word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;42. &lt;em&gt;scoth-&lt;/em&gt; I resolve as &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/36595&#34;&gt;scothach&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “flowery, bushy, tufted”, a good descriptor of the cloud &lt;em&gt;nel&lt;/em&gt; that precedes it. The final letter ‘h’ with a macron is unusual, since most lenition in this manuscript is indicated by a &lt;em&gt;fada&lt;/em&gt; over the letter instead. Yet a few lines earlier, right before the poem’s beginning, there is another h-with-macron at the end of the word which Stokes renders as &lt;em&gt;timchell&lt;/em&gt;. So the h-with-macron is used to show lenition as well as a common ending that could be multiple letters in length. Therefore, we can select the most reasonable ending from eDIL and apply it, which to me is &lt;em&gt;scothach&lt;/em&gt;, giving us “fluffy clouds”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;43. The first element is clearly &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/41608&#34;&gt;tre&lt;/a&gt;, “through”, followed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/41798&#34;&gt;tren&lt;/a&gt;, “strong”, but then we find a ‘c’, a macron, and a suffix &lt;em&gt;-daib&lt;/em&gt;. Thurneysen renders this as &lt;em&gt;cerdaib&lt;/em&gt;, meaning “arts”, which I am not opposed to. The macron allows for an arbitrary letter or string of letters to fill in, but whatever is there should be something monosyllabic, as this seems to be the typical use of other macrons. eDIL offers some examples of words that fit this description: “chladaib”, “chlandaib”, “cruadaib”, “cerdaib”, “cendaib”, etc. But the meaning of “cerdaib” fits well in Lugh’s oration, giving us &lt;em&gt;trie trén cerdaib druag&lt;/em&gt; “through strong druid arts”. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/15847&#34;&gt;2 día&lt;/a&gt; for occurrences of the phrase &lt;em&gt;cerdaib dé druidechtai&lt;/em&gt;, which seems to be a common phrase that is echoed here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;45. This compound word, &lt;em&gt;nimcredbod&lt;/em&gt;, is likely &lt;em&gt;ni + me +&lt;/em&gt; (a form of) &lt;em&gt;credbaid&lt;/em&gt;. The passage in this poem is cited directly in the eDIL entry for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/12821&#34;&gt;credbaid&lt;/a&gt;. Also, a nearly identical formation appears in the &lt;em&gt;Cath Airtig&lt;/em&gt; text presented in &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/eriu_1916_8/page/172/mode/1up&#34;&gt;Ériu 8, pg. 172&lt;/a&gt;, which gives a similar magical song; there it appears as &lt;em&gt;nom credbad&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;credbod&lt;/em&gt; is the verbal noun of &lt;em&gt;credbaid&lt;/em&gt;, and when combined with the next word &lt;em&gt;catha&lt;/em&gt;, gives the meaning of “battle does not wither/weary/corrode me”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;47. This word is much compacted, using two superscript marks to abbreviate. Previously when the scribe had used a mark over an ‘f’, Stokes took it to mean ‘fr’ or even ‘fri’, so I will defer to his interpretation. He transcribes the mark below as &lt;em&gt;friu&lt;/em&gt; a few pages previously: &lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;FRIU.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; class=&#34;same-size&#34; style=&#34;width: 225px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;48. I take this as a verbal form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33129&#34;&gt;3 ness&lt;/a&gt;, which in the eDIL entry references O’Davoren’s Glossary which equates &lt;em&gt;nes .i. crecht&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/12800&#34;&gt;Crecht&lt;/a&gt; has an established meaning of “wound”, and the verb &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33134&#34;&gt;nesaigid&lt;/a&gt; means the same. Or the form &lt;em&gt;nesit&lt;/em&gt; may be the 3rd. person singular of a verb &lt;em&gt;nesaid&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;nessa&lt;/em&gt; which is unlisted in eDIL, but which the scribe may have neologized from the listed word &lt;em&gt;ness&lt;/em&gt;, which is common in Old Irish (see Thurneysen’s &lt;em&gt;A Grammar of Old Irish&lt;/em&gt; section 524, on adjectives turning into verbs). But as regards the macron over the final ‘t’, I suspect this is a final ‘-he’ or ‘-ha’ which would present us with an imperfect passive form of &lt;em&gt;nesaigid&lt;/em&gt;, being &lt;em&gt;nesithe&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;nesitha&lt;/em&gt;, “were wounded”. The more proper form, however, would be &lt;em&gt;nestae&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;nestha&lt;/em&gt;, so I am not utterly convinced of this reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;49. To me the most probable established word compatible here is &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/31755&#34;&gt;meide&lt;/a&gt;, meaning the trunk of a neck and figuratively a corpse; I view it as most probable because we have instances in eDIL of this word appearing as &lt;em&gt;mede&lt;/em&gt;, e.g. &lt;em&gt;méde fri méde&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;médhe&lt;/em&gt;. With &lt;em&gt;nesit-&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;nesitha&lt;/em&gt; as a past participle, we could read “corpses were wounded”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;50. &lt;em&gt;midige&lt;/em&gt; is given in the eDIL listing as an adjective in &lt;em&gt;do thig na mná mídige&lt;/em&gt; “the valiant women came”. We can take this as a spelling variant, applying to the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;51. Mees’ translation renders this line &lt;em&gt;fornem airces&lt;/em&gt; “Such splendor which slays”. He considers &lt;em&gt;fornem&lt;/em&gt; as one word, where I consider it &lt;em&gt;for + nem&lt;/em&gt;. Further, he then interprets the word as &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/23821&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;forníam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which I grant is entirely plausible due to scribal variation, but which, according eDIL, is a different word from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/23813&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;fornem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; itself. Still, the eDIL entry links the meaning back to “heaven”, so if he wanted to avoid this interpretation in order to make sense of the sentence, he may be right. As for &lt;em&gt;airces&lt;/em&gt;, it is a form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/1779&#34;&gt;aircisid&lt;/a&gt; with an unusual &lt;em&gt;-es&lt;/em&gt; ending; however, see in Note 53 that this &lt;em&gt;-es&lt;/em&gt; ending is used for a 3rd person singular present indicative, so I will render it as “meets”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;52. &lt;em&gt;lúachoir&lt;/em&gt; here can either mean “rushes”, the plant, which burn quite ferociously when dry, or “brightness”, the end result of fire. Either are good candidates for what burns here; however, since the previous formulation implies “meeting &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt;” or “attaining &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; heaven”, I will take this word as meaning “burning &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; brightness”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;53. A form of &lt;em&gt;loiscid&lt;/em&gt; with an &lt;em&gt;-es&lt;/em&gt; ending is hard to find documented, but it appears in &lt;em&gt;Ériu&lt;/em&gt; Vol. VII, pg. 160, in the following sentence: &lt;em&gt;is besad in tineth is cuma &lt;strong&gt;loisces&lt;/strong&gt; a mbis issa ⁊ huasa ⁊ inna erchomair&lt;/em&gt;, translated by Gwynn as “For it is the way of fire that it &lt;strong&gt;burns&lt;/strong&gt; indifferently what is below and above and near it”. &lt;em&gt;loisces&lt;/em&gt; is given as a simple 3rd person singular present indicative, so I will render it the same here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;54. &lt;em&gt;mar&lt;/em&gt; here is unresolved, and &lt;em&gt;tal-&lt;/em&gt; here is unresolved with a macron ending. The strange crossbar under the ‘a’ in the manuscript is seen elsewhere and Stokes resolves this symbol to be an ‘r’, giving &lt;em&gt;martal-&lt;/em&gt;. Given that Word 56 is clearly &lt;em&gt;martorainn&lt;/em&gt;, we can take this as a pattern which consists of &lt;em&gt;mar&lt;/em&gt; + a disyllabic word beginning with ‘t’, and followed by a disyllabic verb. So we can then fill in the macron with the most expected ending for a word beginning with &lt;em&gt;tal-&lt;/em&gt;, which would yield the word &lt;em&gt;talam&lt;/em&gt;, “land, earth”. This fits nicely with the meaning of the next word, &lt;em&gt;tshuides&lt;/em&gt; “sits”. &lt;em&gt;mar&lt;/em&gt; can mean either “as” or “great”, giving us either “as the earth sits” or “the great earth sits”. Since &lt;em&gt;mar&lt;/em&gt;, even in modern Irish, precedes the clause it acts upon, while &lt;em&gt;már&lt;/em&gt; is an adjective that should come after the noun &lt;em&gt;talam&lt;/em&gt;, I lean towards the former interpretation. &lt;em&gt;mar&lt;/em&gt; meaning “as, such as” is also a development of Middle Irish, and so the other markers of Middle Irish in this poem allow us to take this word with its later meaning (see Stifter’s &lt;em&gt;Sengoídelc&lt;/em&gt; pp. 308).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;59. Although &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10641&#34;&gt;comaircid&lt;/a&gt; has a hard ‘k’ sound in the final ‘c’, the listing for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10674&#34;&gt;comairser&lt;/a&gt; wonders if &lt;em&gt;comaircid&lt;/em&gt; can take forms, probably in the subjunctive, with a final ‘s’ sound instead. &lt;em&gt;mad fris gais comairser&lt;/em&gt; “if thou consult wisdom”, under &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/24352&#34;&gt;fris-comairc&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps this is a development in Middle Irish: we already see a ‘c’ and ‘s’ close together in &lt;em&gt;comaircsead&lt;/em&gt; in the main listing. Perhaps palatalization is also at play. So I take this word to be a subjunctive 3rd person form of &lt;em&gt;comaircid&lt;/em&gt;. I take its meaning as “cry out”. An alternative is a compound of &lt;em&gt;com&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/4287&#34;&gt;airsid&lt;/a&gt;, but with an unclear meaning “with + aged, veteran”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;60. The final piece, &lt;em&gt;naie&lt;/em&gt;, is unknown, but my best estimation is that it derives from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33235&#34;&gt;nae&lt;/a&gt;, “person”.  The alternatives are &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33243&#34;&gt;noí&lt;/a&gt;, “nine”, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33205&#34;&gt;noe&lt;/a&gt;, “boat”, but there seems to be sufficient spelling variation in the &lt;em&gt;nae&lt;/em&gt; entry for this to be acceptable. And see this line in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33235&#34;&gt;eDIL entry&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;fercheirtní .i. fír cert naí .i. duine fīr-cherte&lt;/em&gt;, which gives &lt;em&gt;fercheirtní&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;fer cheirt ní&lt;/em&gt;, a triple word construction similar to &lt;em&gt;fricechnaie&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;fri cech nai&lt;/em&gt;. The unaccounted-for final ‘e’ may then be merely a dialectical variation. This word appears similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33151&#34;&gt;niae&lt;/a&gt;, Word 76, but every form of this word begins with an ‘i’ and never a broad vowel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;61. &lt;em&gt;go&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;comair&lt;/em&gt; both indicate direction and meeting, so I translate this as “before”, indicating the listener approaching up to Ogma, sun and moon, earth and heaven, and standing before each. Under &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/10630&#34;&gt;comair&lt;/a&gt; we see an identical formulation: &lt;em&gt;co comor&lt;/em&gt; “as far as opposite”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;64. I cannot identify a solid translation of this word in this form. Mees renders it as “and also”; Carmody renders it as “good-hound”; LLMs similarly provide &lt;em&gt;sa-chú&lt;/em&gt; as a guess. All unsatisfactory. I instead search for a homophonic word which is a reasonable candidate. We could read this word as &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/35927&#34;&gt;saich&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “bad, evil”, hardly an epithet of Ogma; &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/38232&#34;&gt;sochar&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “a valid legal contract”, a nonsensical meaning; &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/36069&#34;&gt;saíthiud&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “a fraud”, being unlikely; a form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/36063&#34;&gt;sáithech&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “satisfied (of appetite)”, which lists a homophonic comparative form &lt;em&gt;sathchu&lt;/em&gt;; or my preferred &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/38252&#34;&gt;sochonn&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “wise”. This word &lt;em&gt;sochonn&lt;/em&gt; lists a form as &lt;em&gt;sochuinn&lt;/em&gt;, very near to our &lt;em&gt;sachu&lt;/em&gt; save for a swapped vowel and a missing ending. I choose to use this word mainly on meaning in addition to phonetic similarity, as it is very proper to describe Ogma as wise, who is called a &lt;em&gt;treinfer&lt;/em&gt;, “champion”, of the &lt;em&gt;Tuatha Dé&lt;/em&gt;. Ultimately this word’s translation remains open to improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;72. See the eDIL entry for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/26628&#34;&gt;grían&lt;/a&gt;, which lists this as an example of the dative case of the word: &lt;em&gt;hi coimthect du gréin ┐ escu&lt;/em&gt;; the exact formulation we have here. It clearly means “sun and moon”; see &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/20410&#34;&gt;ésca&lt;/a&gt;, which helps illuminates the phrase as it appears here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;79. Note that in this word, we see the same subscripted ‘i’ that appears often after an ‘s’, as in &lt;em&gt;dreimsie&lt;/em&gt;. I will take this word to mean “black”, and describe a “black host”, but a figurative meaning of &lt;em&gt;duib&lt;/em&gt; is listed as “great, expressing intensity”, thus the line could also be “my host is a great host”, which is identical is meaning to the following line &lt;em&gt;mo slúag so slúag mor&lt;/em&gt;. Mees takes this word as the pronoun equivalent to Mod. Ir. &lt;em&gt;daoibh&lt;/em&gt; “to you all,” but I disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;84. This word has two possibilities to me: the first part can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32411&#34;&gt;moch&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/32422&#34;&gt;mochta&lt;/a&gt;, and the second part either &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/35988&#34;&gt;saílech&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/35989&#34;&gt;saílechtu&lt;/a&gt;. Both of the latter words mean “hope” or “thoughtful” in some form. &lt;em&gt;Moch&lt;/em&gt; is given as “early, speedy”, and &lt;em&gt;mochta&lt;/em&gt; is given as “mighty, great”. So the two possibilities then are 1) “early-thoughtful”, “quick-thoughtful”, perhaps “quickwitted” or 2) “mighty-thoughtful”, “greatly-thoughtful”, perhaps “strongminded”. When imagining this epithet applied to an eager army, I can only imagine that strength is emphasized over wit, so I prefer to render this word as “resolute” or “steadfast”. Also, if one chose to prefer &lt;em&gt;moch&lt;/em&gt; over &lt;em&gt;mocht&lt;/em&gt;, one would also have to account for the lost ‘t’ in &lt;em&gt;mochtsailech&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;86. Examples of the o-form of &lt;em&gt;aire&lt;/em&gt;/&lt;em&gt;airech&lt;/em&gt; can be seen in the entry for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/1885&#34;&gt;3 aire&lt;/a&gt;. eDIL also specifies that &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/33116&#34;&gt;nert&lt;/a&gt; can become adjectival when used as the primary element in a compound, with some examples, &lt;em&gt;co nertbáig&lt;/em&gt; “with strong fight”, &lt;em&gt;nertbla&lt;/em&gt; “mighty fame”, etc. Thus we have “mighty lords”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;87. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/16842&#34;&gt;díth&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;em&gt;rogenair [Isu] ó Muire&lt;/em&gt;, “Jesus born of Mary”, and under &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/25186&#34;&gt;gainithir&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;is hé Crist rogenir&lt;/em&gt;, “Christ is born”; &lt;em&gt;Rí rogenair imBetheil&lt;/em&gt;, “King born in Bethlehem”; etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;89. The meaning of &lt;em&gt;da-&lt;/em&gt; as “two” is supported by &lt;em&gt;etir&lt;/em&gt;: “between” implies two things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;90. The macron in this word indicates an &lt;em&gt;-or&lt;/em&gt;, as in previous word with an f-macron. See &lt;em&gt;forslecht&lt;/em&gt; (9) or &lt;em&gt;forandechraiged&lt;/em&gt; (28). This occurrence, and the &lt;em&gt;arotroi&lt;/em&gt; succeeding it, are listed in the entry for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/4919&#34;&gt;at-roí&lt;/a&gt;, meaning “to fail”, with an unclear meaning. Isolde Carmody has seemingly accepted this association wholeheartedly, and translates &lt;em&gt;arotroi, arotrai&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;ataforroi&lt;/em&gt; as variations of the word “fail”; but this association seems tenuous, brought about by hitting a dead end regarding &lt;em&gt;arotroi&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ataforroi&lt;/em&gt;. Note 1 establishes &lt;em&gt;Arotroi&lt;/em&gt; as “Arise!”, but &lt;em&gt;ataforroi&lt;/em&gt; seems unrelated. Instead, I take it as &lt;em&gt;atá&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;forroi&lt;/em&gt;, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/22676&#34;&gt;fo-fich&lt;/a&gt;, which lists &lt;em&gt;forroi&lt;/em&gt; as its 3rd person present singular subjunctive form, ultimately implying that the subject may or hypothetically could attack, or which Lugh desires to attack. Thus, “which attacks” or even “poised to charge”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Translation&#34;&gt;Translation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atroroi cat comartan isincathirgal robris comlondo forslechtaib slúaig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;silsiter riasluag sioabrai iath fer fomnai. cuife&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cithai fir genrogain lentor gala. fordomaisit fordomcloisid foran&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dechraiged fir duib becc find nomtainn. fó fó fé fé clé amainsi no&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;efita máime iernelscothach trietrencerdaib druag. Nimcredbod catha fricricha&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nesitha mede midege fornemairces forluachoir loisces martalam tṡuides&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;martorainn trogais. Nicomairsid fricechnaie gocomair ogma sachu go&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;comair nem 7 talam go comair grioan 7 esqu. Drem níadh modremsie duib.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mo slúagso slúag mor murnech mochtsailech bruithe nertoirech rogenoir&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;etir dacri ataforroi cath comortai. arotroi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arise! Mutual battle in war-fury furiously overthrows the hewing hosts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lands of watchful men will be thrown down before the frenzied army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A den of sheep are men without wills which adhere to war-fury. Over-cunning,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over-hearkening, over-distinguished men, dark, few, bright, on a holy-raid. Joy! Joy! Woe! Woe! Evil! Thusly so! A handful of divine food&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the tufted clouds through strong druid arts. Battle against a land does not weary me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Valiant corpses were wounded reaching heaven, burning to brilliance, as the earth sits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the thunder comes forth. Do not cry out to each one before wise Ogma,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before heaven and earth, before sun and moon. My dark troop is a troop of warriors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My army is a great army, uproarious, steadfast, boiling, mighty as lords, born&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between two bodies which attack in battle of mutual slaughter. Arise!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Meter-or-Arranging-the-Lines&#34;&gt;Meter, or Arranging the Lines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This incantation is a &lt;em&gt;rosc&lt;/em&gt; poem, which typically in the Old Irish period consist of four-line stanzas with any number, but most often seven, syllables in each line, with alliteration within each line and each line rhyming within the stanza. As such, we can attempt to fit the text into the &lt;em&gt;rosc&lt;/em&gt; pattern and see if it fits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the curious reader wants a primer on Old Irish poetry, he should seek out Lesson 58 in David Stifter’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/SengodelcOldIrishForBeginn&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sengoídelc: Old Irish for Beginners&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which goes over meter, rhyme, stanzas, syllable count, cadence, etc. One point I’d like to lift from that text to this one is the following: “Whereas in [English or German] the rhyming portions of words must be absolutely identical, there is much more freedom is Irish poetry… Rhyme starts with the stressed vowel… the two vowels must both be either short or long; a short vowel does not rhyme with a long one.” He offers a footnote: “In Middle Irish, after unstressed vowels had become /ə/, all finals vowels, whatever their origin, rhyme with each other.” Since this &lt;em&gt;rosc&lt;/em&gt; shows clear signs of composition in Middle Irish, we can keep this rhyme qualification in mind. I should also note that in Old and Middle Irish, stress mot often falls on the first syllable of the word, unless that syllable is a common preposition that is not the root. For example, COMartan, MURNech, MIDege, SILsiter, but also foraNDECHraiged, nimCREDbod, genROGain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Line&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Syllables&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Atroroi cat comartan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;isin cathirgal robris&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comlondo forslechtaib slúaig&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;silsiter riasluag sioabrai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;iath fer fomnai.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cuifecithai&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fir genrogain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;lentor gala.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fordomaisit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fordomcloisid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;forandechraiged&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fir duib becc find&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;nomtainn. fó fó fé fé&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;clé amainsi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;noefita máim&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;iernelscothach&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;trietrencerdaib druag.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nimcredbod catha&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fricricha nesitha&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mede midege&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;fornemairces&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;forluachoir loisces&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;martalam tṡuides&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;martorainn trogais.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nicomairsid fricechnaie&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;go comair ogma sachu&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;go comair nem ⁊ talam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;go comair grioan ⁊ esqu&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Drem níadh mo dremsie duib&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mo sluagso sluag mor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;murnech mochtsailech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bruithe nertoirech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rogenoir etir dacri&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ataforroi&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;cath comortai. arotrai.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stanza starting with &lt;em&gt;Nicomairsid&lt;/em&gt; is an anchor point in the incantation: it cleanly contains four perfect lines of seven syllables each, similar to the first stanza &lt;em&gt;Arotroi&lt;/em&gt;. All other lines can be fit between these two. It seems that in this &lt;em&gt;rosc&lt;/em&gt;, syllable count is not so strict. Arranging lines by rhyme, we see that the syllable count switches between 4, 5, 6, and 7 per line throughout the poem, with certain lines breaking the pattern (&lt;em&gt;forandechraiged&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;fornemairces&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;nomtainn&lt;/em&gt;), along with the final three(?) lines which don’t seem to rhyme or fit. It is possible that these aberrant words underwent elision on weak letters to shorten them or hiatus to extend them, e.g. &lt;em&gt;forandechrai&lt;strong&gt;g&lt;/strong&gt;ed&lt;/em&gt; (5) -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;forandechrai&lt;strong&gt;gh&lt;/strong&gt;ed&lt;/em&gt; (5) -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;forandechraied&lt;/em&gt; (4). But these aberrant lines are the exception to an otherwise regular meter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to ignore rhyme and arrange the poem into stanzas of perfect seven syllable lines, though it is less satisfactory, however the lines I’ve proposed are also quite unsatisfactory. It appears that this poem is simply not regularly composed in rhyme or syllable count. Mees calls the middle section ‘garbled… copied… from a much earlier manuscript’; I was struck with the impression that the scribe may have had this poem read aloud to him by another person. Either way, this is a difficult poem which remains open to amendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also appears to be a poem composed in an Old Irish fashion, but modernized to Middle Irish through the use of new words, new forms of words, new uses for old words, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my version in English:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arise! Mutual battle&lt;br&gt;
in war-fury overthrows&lt;br&gt;
furiously the hewing hosts,&lt;br&gt;
the lands of watchful men&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;will be thrown down before the frenzied army.&lt;br&gt;
A den of sheep&lt;br&gt;
are men without wills&lt;br&gt;
which adhere to war-fury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over-cunning,&lt;br&gt;
Over-hearkening,&lt;br&gt;
over-distinguished&lt;br&gt;
men, dark, few, bright,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;on a holy-raid. Joy! Joy! Woe! Woe!&lt;br&gt;
Evil! Thusly so!&lt;br&gt;
A handful of divine food&lt;br&gt;
Across the tufted clouds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;through strong druid arts.&lt;br&gt;
Battle against a land&lt;br&gt;
does not weary me,&lt;br&gt;
valiant corpses were wounded&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;reaching heaven,&lt;br&gt;
burning to brilliance,&lt;br&gt;
as the earth sits,&lt;br&gt;
as the thunder comes forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not cry out to each one&lt;br&gt;
before wise Ogma,&lt;br&gt;
before heaven and earth,&lt;br&gt;
before sun and moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My dark troop is a troop of warriors.&lt;br&gt;
My army is a great army,&lt;br&gt;
uproarious, steadfast,&lt;br&gt;
boiling, mighty lords&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;are born between two bodies&lt;br&gt;
which attack&lt;br&gt;
in battle of mutual slaughter. Arise!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;An-Instance-of-Corrguinecht&#34;&gt;An Instance of &lt;em&gt;Corrguinecht&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chant is more prominent than the others in the &lt;em&gt;Cath&lt;/em&gt; due to the unusual stance which Lugh takes while reciting it: one-eyed, one-legged, and one-armed, circling the &lt;em&gt;Tuatha Dé&lt;/em&gt; army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wherefore then Lugh sang this chant below, as he went round the men of Erin, on one foot and with one eye (closed):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cath Maige Tuired 129&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Stokes&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This posture is known in the scholarship as &lt;em&gt;corrguinecht&lt;/em&gt;, and is translated in the non-academic space as “crane pose”, drawing similarities between standing on one leg and a crane’s resting pose, drawn from the word &lt;em&gt;corr&lt;/em&gt; “crane, heron”, and &lt;em&gt;guin&lt;/em&gt; “wounding, harming”. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.interesly.com/medieval-irish-cursing/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; for this etymology. A more academic etymology uses the alternate meaning of &lt;a href=&#34;https://dil.ie/12513&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;corr&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “point, peak, sharp object”, reminiscent of a crane’s beak but also of needles or weapons. The song itself is identified as &lt;em&gt;glám dícenn&lt;/em&gt;, or “satire of two points”, which is also used by Coipre mac Etaín &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/revueceltique12pari/page/70/mode/2up&#34;&gt;earlier&lt;/a&gt; in the story against Bres of the Fomorians. These two magical rituals, one of speech and the other of posture, are purportedly related here and elsewhere but seem not to be the same thing: they can be performed separately and serve separate functions. The stance then, I suspect, is an amplifier of the incantation, and the incantation is used to raise the spirits of the &lt;em&gt;Tuatha Dé&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;glám dícenn&lt;/em&gt; is typically used as a curse, in fact Coipre mac Etaín lists is &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/revueceltique12pari/page/90/mode/2up&#34;&gt;here in 115.&lt;/a&gt; as a weapon to be used against the Fomorians, but Lugh uses it for the benefit of his own army thus implying that the ritual is neutral, and the speech itself makes it a blessing or a curse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the better etymology for &lt;em&gt;corrguinecht&lt;/em&gt; as “wounding with points”, we still must account for Lugh’s mysterious stance here, which I am inclined to believe still relates to the crane or heron and its role as a bird which traverses land, heaven, and sea (i.e. the underworld). A singer invoking the crane or contorting his spirit to become a crane-spirit during a ritual would thus be taking on this cosmological quality for the amplification of his magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;corrguinecht&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;glám dícenn&lt;/em&gt; will be treated in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/The-Song-of-Lugh/Crane.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Further-Reading&#34;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Medieval Manuscripts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://guides.loc.gov/manuscript-facsimiles/deciphering-scribal-abbreviations#s-lib-ctab-24229924-8&#34;&gt;Deciphering Scribal Abbreviations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.ualberta.ca/~sreimer/ms-course/course/punc.htm&#34;&gt;Manuscript Studies - Punctuation and Other Symbols&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://spotlight.vatlib.it/latin-paleography/feature/10-1-insular-majuscule-or-round-insular&#34;&gt;Insular Script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Old Irish:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/thurneysen-a-grammar-of-old-irish&#34;&gt;A Grammar of Old Irish&lt;/a&gt; by Rudolf Thurneysen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/conciseoldirishg01pokouoft&#34;&gt;A Concise Old Irish Grammar and Reader&lt;/a&gt; by Julius Pokorny&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;em&gt;Cath Maige Tuired&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://people.umass.edu/sharris/in/handouts/Cath_Maige_Tuired.pdf&#34;&gt;Elizabeth Gray’s Translation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Irish Magic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/celtic-curses/1C98E6A5F9E316AC729361BC9D245890&#34;&gt;Celtic Curses&lt;/a&gt; by Bernard Mees&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/past/article/247/1/113/5721469&#34;&gt;Irish Cursing and the Art of Magic, 1750–2018&lt;/a&gt; by Thomas Waters&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="Magic" />
        <category term="Old Irish" />
        <updated>2025-10-27T00:55:39.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/Nine-Herbs-Charm/</id>
        <title>Nine Herbs Charm</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/Nine-Herbs-Charm/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;https://cdn.jsdelivr.net/hint.css/2.4.1/hint.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Nine-Herbs-Charm/Anglo-SaxonWarrior.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Anglo-Saxon Warrior&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My reading of the Anglo-Saxon Nine Herbs Charm or 𝘕𝘪𝘨𝘰𝘯 𝘞𝘺𝘳𝘵𝘢 𝘎𝘢𝘭𝘥𝘰𝘳, which is one of the few Anglo-Saxon magical and medical texts that survives. It brings Woden and Christ into the same text, among many other esoteric passages. The Nine Herbs Charm was translated by Oswald Cockayne in 1866, seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/leechdomswortcun03cock/page/30/mode/2up&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and recently by Joseph Hopkins for &lt;a href=&#34;http://mimmisbrunnr.info&#34;&gt;mimmisbrunnr.info&lt;/a&gt; in 2020, seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mimisbrunnr.info/nigon-wyrta-galdor&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and there are a few contentious points that people disagree on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Herbs-and-Disease&#34;&gt;Herbs and Disease&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of you will be interested in Woden, the glory-twigs, and the seven worlds, but this is foremost a medicinal text. The nine herbs are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;𝘔𝘶𝘤𝘨𝘸𝘺𝘳𝘵 - Mugwort&lt;br&gt;
𝘞𝘦𝘨𝘣𝘳𝘢𝘥𝘦 “Waybread” - Plantain&lt;br&gt;
𝘚𝘵𝘶𝘯𝘦 - Lamb’s Cress&lt;br&gt;
𝘈𝘵𝘵𝘰𝘳𝘭𝘢ð𝘦 - Fumitory&lt;br&gt;
𝘔æ𝘨ðe - Chamomile&lt;br&gt;
𝘞𝘦𝘳𝘨𝘶𝘭𝘶 - Nettle&lt;br&gt;
Æ𝘱𝘱𝘦𝘭 - Crab Apple&lt;br&gt;
𝘍𝘪𝘭𝘭𝘦 - Chervil&lt;br&gt;
𝘍𝘪𝘯𝘶𝘭𝘦 - Fennel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text names the plant and sings the virtues of each, but the plant list is debated since the poem is unclear, some names may not be names. And in the prose section after the poem, the author changes the nine herbs: &lt;em&gt;stune&lt;/em&gt; becomes lambscress, &lt;em&gt;wergulu&lt;/em&gt; becomes nettle. But we know there are nine since in the prose he says there are 𝘯𝘺𝘨𝘰𝘯 𝘸𝘺𝘳𝘵𝘢, nine worts, which prevail against the nine venoms and nine “flying vile things”. The herbs are conceived of as nine types of soldier, warriors of the plant world, which war against poison, and which were placed in the world by the Lord (Christ or Woden). This warband of plants is led by the heavenly Lord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poison and disease are thought of as invisible serpents that writhe across the land, or swarms of flies in the air. They are called “loathful ones”, 𝘸𝘺𝘳𝘮.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;þu miht ƿiþ attre&lt;br&gt;
⁊ ƿið onflyge&lt;br&gt;
þu miht ƿiþ þa laþan&lt;br&gt;
ðe geond lond færð&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
For venom availest,&lt;br&gt;
For flying vile things;&lt;br&gt;
Mighty against loathed ones&lt;br&gt;
That through the land rove.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lines 9-12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Cockayne&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each herb has some inner strength that destroys or nullifies the venom of these malevolent spirits which wreak disease, if prepared the right way. Here it instructs the reciter to make a salve of the herbs, fennel, ashes, water, and egg, then to bathe the wound in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mugwort, waybroad which spreadeth open towards the east, lambscress, attorlothe, maythen, nettle, crab apple, chervil, fennel, and old soap; work the worts to a dust, mingle with the soap and with the verjuice of the apple; form a slop of water and of ashes, take fennel, boil it in the slop, and foment with egg mixture, when the man puts on the salve, either before or after. Sing the charm upon each of the worts; thrice before “he” works them up, and over the apple in like manner; and sing into the mans mouth and into both his ears the same magic song, and into the wound, before he applies the salve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paragraph 46&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Cockayne&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is ancient herb-medicine. In Ireland at around this time (10th century), doctors had divided medicine into herb-medicine (pharmacology), knife-medicine (surgery), and song-medicine (prayer/chanting), which were the three methods available to ancient doctors: chemical intervention, surgical intervention, or lifestyle change. This entire charm is meant to be sung, hence why we call it the nine herbs 𝘨𝘢𝘭𝘥𝘰𝘳 or song. In fact, in the previous excerpt, we are specifically instructed to sing this charm to the herbs, and into the victim’s mouth and ears, and into the wound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disease was seen as something which lingers high in the air, in cold, wet places, or within animals and plants which hate mankind, caused by malevolent spirits and which overtake people suddenly. A sickness must be weakened, then banished. Here, venom is something to be “blown away”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Motan ealle weoda nu ƿyrtum aspringan&lt;br&gt;
sæs toslupan, eal sealt ƿæter&lt;br&gt;
ðonne ic þis attor of ðe geblaƿe&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
All weeds now may Give way to worts.&lt;br&gt;
Seas may dissolve, All salt water,&lt;br&gt;
when I this venom from thee blow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paragraph 45&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Cockayne&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor is to blow the venom (or its evil spirit) out of the body, and then into something else, like the endless salty sea or a useless weed (𝘸𝘦𝘰𝘥𝘢) where it cannot do harm. It was the common view in most pre-modern societies that many things seen and unseen in the world were hostile to Man, and that an ally god would lead us in opposing these wild forces. For that reason he gave us the herbs, and taught us to use them. Chervil and Fennel, the author says, are mighty against pain, venom, a fiend’s hand, great guile, against small, bewitching wights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;earmum and eadigum&lt;br&gt;
eallum to bote&lt;br&gt;
Stond heo ƿið ƿærce,&lt;br&gt;
stunað heo ƿið attre&lt;br&gt;
seo mæg ƿið * III&lt;br&gt;
⁊ wið XXX&lt;br&gt;
ƿið feondes hond&lt;br&gt;
ƿið frea begde&lt;br&gt;
ƿið malscrunge&lt;br&gt;
minra wihta&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
For the poor and the rich,&lt;br&gt;
Panacea for all.&lt;br&gt;
It standeth against pain&lt;br&gt;
It stoundeth at venom,&lt;br&gt;
Strong it is gainst three&lt;br&gt;
And against thirty;&lt;br&gt;
Gainst the hand of the fiend,&lt;br&gt;
(To the Lord low it louted)&lt;br&gt;
Gainst foul fascination&lt;br&gt;
Of farm stock of mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lines 74-86&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Cockayne&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: the word ‘wihta’ is here translated by Cockayne as ‘farm-stock’, but truly just means ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/wiht#Old_English&#34;&gt;thing, creature&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Nine-Herbs-Charm/Demon.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Saint John the Evangelist on Patmos by Master of the Rotterdam Saint John on Patmos&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Saint John the Evangelist on Patmos, c. 1475&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Wuldortanas&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wuldortanas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ðas VIIII ongon&lt;br&gt;
ƿið nygon attrum.&lt;br&gt;
ⵜǷyrm com snican,&lt;br&gt;
toslat he nan&lt;br&gt;
ða genam Ƿoden&lt;br&gt;
* VIIII * ƿuldortanas&lt;br&gt;
sloh ða þa næddran&lt;br&gt;
þæt heo on VIIII * tofleah&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
These nine can march on&lt;br&gt;
Gainst nine ugly poisons.&lt;br&gt;
A worm sneaking came&lt;br&gt;
To slay and to slaughter;&lt;br&gt;
Then took up Woden&lt;br&gt;
Nine wondrous twigs,&lt;br&gt;
He smote then the nadder&lt;br&gt;
Till it flew in nine bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Line 59-66&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Cockayne&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woden is named as leading the attack against the hostile 𝘸𝘺𝘳𝘮, taking nine glory-twigs 𝘸𝘶𝘭𝘥𝘰𝘳𝘵𝘢𝘯𝘢𝘴 and killing the serpent with them, diving it into nine pieces, and letting the crabapple dilute its venom. These glory-twigs are completely unknown. They could be pieces of wood carved with runes or other magical symbols, which are not unknown in the Germanic and Indo-European world. Tacitus &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0083%3Achapter%3D10&#34;&gt;says&lt;/a&gt; that ancient Germans used boughs of a fruit tree, cut into pieces and carved with markings, which aid in divination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use of the lots is simple. A little bough is lopped off a fruit-bearing tree, and cut into small pieces; these are distinguished by certain marks, and thrown carelessly and at random over a white garment. In public questions the priest of the particular state, in private the father of the family, invokes the gods, and, with his eyes towards heaven, takes up each piece three times, and finds in them a meaning according to the mark previously impressed on them. If they prove unfavourable, there is no further consultation that day about the matter; if they sanction it, the confirmation of augury is still required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Germania&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Chapter 10&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canterbury Charm is a runic marginal note calling on Thor to eliminate disease.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;See Cotton MS Caligula A XV in the British Library, folio [123v](https://iiif.bl.uk/uv/#?manifest=https://bl.digirati.io/iiif/ark:/81055/vdc_100058106204.0x000001) and [124r](https://iiif.bl.uk/uv/#?manifest=https://bl.digirati.io/iiif/ark:/81055/vdc_100058106204.0x000001).
&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The fact that the Canterbury Charm had to be written in the margins of an unrelated text implies that the very act of being written down or carved was an essential part of the power of runes—writing itself as invocation. Perhaps Woden used runes and magic to banish the malignant spirits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Nine-Herbs-Charm/CanterburyCharm.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Canterbury Charm and its Runes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Canterbury Charm in Manuscript and Transcribed&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gyril wound-causer, go now! You are found. May Thor bless you, lord of ogres! Gyril wound-causer. Against blood-vessel pus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Canterbury Charm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Macleod and Mees&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the origins of the Irish ogham script is in carvings onto wood. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/auraicept00calduoft/page/272/mode/2up&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Auraicept na n-Eces&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; relates that the god Ogma created the alphabet by carving seven Bs into a strip of birch wood:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;This moreover is the first thing that was written by Ogham, b was written, and to convey a warning to Lug son of Ethliu it was written respecting his wife lest she should be carried away from him into faeryland, to wit, seven b’s in one switch of birch&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Auraicept na n-Eces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Calder 1917&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or the nine 𝘸𝘶𝘭𝘥𝘦𝘳𝘵𝘢𝘯𝘢𝘴 could be the nine herbs themselves, which would fit with the repetition of the number nine in the preceding lines. Ultimately it will be impossible to know for sure, as with many ancient mysteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Nine-Herbs-Charm/Tree.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Woden-⁊-Christ&#34;&gt;Woden ⁊ Christ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;ða genam Ƿoden * VIIII * ƿuldortanas&lt;br&gt;
sloh ða þa næddran þæt heo on VIIII * tofleah&lt;br&gt;
Þær geændade æppel and attor&lt;br&gt;
…&lt;br&gt;
ⵜFille and finule, felamihtigu twa&lt;br&gt;
þa ƿyrte gesceop ƿitig drihten&lt;br&gt;
halig on heofonum, þa he hongode&lt;br&gt;
sette and sænde on VII ƿorulde&lt;br&gt;
earmum and eadigum eallum to bote&lt;br&gt;
…&lt;br&gt;
ⵜCrist stod ofer adle ængan cundes&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
Then Wōden took VIIII glory-twigs,&lt;br&gt;
struck the serpent,&lt;br&gt;
that she into VIIII flew,&lt;br&gt;
…&lt;br&gt;
ⵜFille and finule, a very mighty two,&lt;br&gt;
these worts the wise lord shaped,&lt;br&gt;
holy in the heavens, while he hung,&lt;br&gt;
set and sent them to VII worlds,&lt;br&gt;
poor and prosperous, as remedy for all.&lt;br&gt;
…&lt;br&gt;
ⵜChrist stood over sickness of every kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lines 63-65 and Paragraph 45&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Hopkins&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mention of Woden and Christ together seems contradictory. Is this a Christian writing down an invocation to a pagan god? Naturally the impassable pagan/Christian divide is mostly a modern invention of neopagans and secularized Christians. Medieval people were not often so discriminatory, calling upon a spirit or God as needed. If Christ seemingly failed them, they might in desperation call upon Woden or Thunor, then revert to Christ, or call upon a countless number of local land spirits, &lt;em&gt;genii locorum&lt;/em&gt;. The author seems to do just this, and even have fun with it, when he leaves ambiguity here. Which wise Lord (𝘸𝘪𝘵𝘪𝘨 𝘥𝘳𝘪𝘩𝘵𝘦𝘯) hangs in heaven, on a cross or on a tree? The same ambiguity is seen in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.csun.edu/~sk36711/WWW/258/DreamofRood.pdf&#34;&gt;Dream of the Rood&lt;/a&gt; which, for one example among many, calls the Cross a “Victory-beam” or “Victory-tree”. Both gods were meant to heal (or destroy evil spirits), and here we can see a melding of belief systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this isn’t a direct attestation of Anglo-Saxon paganism: it is simply a historical account of the ancient origin of the &lt;em&gt;wuldortanas&lt;/em&gt;. Christians like Alfred the Great also preserved Woden in the historical account of his own genealogy,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;See *Historia Brittonum* [here](https://www.gutenberg.org/files/1972/1972-h/1972-h.htm) for the genealogy of English kings c. 850 AD, or the *Anglian Collection of Royal Genealogies* [here](https://www.jstor.org/stable/44510666) c. 800 AD.
&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; tracing his origin to a pre-Christian god but not worshipping that god (perhaps euhemerism was a popular belief).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Nine-Herbs-Charm/Woden.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Woden&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Woden&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Nygon-Naedran&#34;&gt;Nygon Nædran&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ic ana ƿat ea rinnende&lt;br&gt;
þær þa nygon nædran behealdað&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
I alone know water running&lt;br&gt;
where the nine serpents beheld.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paragraph 45&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Hopkins&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the two most esoteric details, which I will struggle to treat somprehensively here. First, this verse that “I alone know a running stream, and the nine adders beware it”. The active verb here is 𝘣𝘦𝘩𝘦𝘢𝘭𝘥𝘢ð, “beholdeth”, but the meaning in Old English could be to hold, to behold, to do, to occupy. What is this running stream, and what are these nine serpents? The connection between serpents and running rivers is especially old, and could encompass a being like Niðhöggr, who in Völuspá and Gylfaginning is described in or near a river or the spring Hvergelmir:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;En svá margir ormar eru í Hvergelmi með Níðhögg, at engi tunga má telja. Svá segir hér:&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
Askr Yggdrasils&lt;br&gt;
drýgir erfiði&lt;br&gt;
meira en menn viti;&lt;br&gt;
hjörtr bítr ofan,&lt;br&gt;
en á hliðu fúnar,&lt;br&gt;
skerðir Níðhöggr neðan.&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
Svá er enn sagt:&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
Ormar fleiri liggja&lt;br&gt;
und aski Yggdrasils&lt;br&gt;
en þat of hyggi hverr ósviðra apa.&lt;br&gt;
Góinn ok Móinn,&lt;br&gt;
þeir eru Grafvitnis synir,&lt;br&gt;
Grábakr ok Grafvölluðr,&lt;br&gt;
Ófnir ok Sváfnir,&lt;br&gt;
hygg ek, at æ myni&lt;br&gt;
meiðs kvistum má.&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
Moreover, so many serpents are in Hvergelmir with Nídhöggr, that no tongue can tell them, as is here said:&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
Ash Yggdrasill | suffers anguish,&lt;br&gt;
More than men know of:&lt;br&gt;
The stag bites above; | on the side it rotteth,&lt;br&gt;
And Nídhöggr gnaws from below.&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
And it is further said:&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
More serpents lie | under Yggdrasill’s stock&lt;br&gt;
Than every unwise ape can think:&lt;br&gt;
Góinn and Móinn | (they’re Grafvitnir’s sons),&lt;br&gt;
Grábakr and Grafvölludr;&lt;br&gt;
Ófnir and Sváfnir | I think shall aye&lt;br&gt;
Tear the trunk’s twigs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gylfaginning 16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Brodeur 1916&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sá hon þar vaða&lt;br&gt;
þunga strauma&lt;br&gt;
menn meinsvara&lt;br&gt;
ok morðvarga&lt;br&gt;
ok þann er annars glepr&lt;br&gt;
eyrarúnu;&lt;br&gt;
þar saug Niðhöggr&lt;br&gt;
nái framgengna,&lt;br&gt;
sleit vargr vera.&lt;br&gt;
Vituð ér enn - eða hvat?&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
I saw there wading | through rivers wild&lt;br&gt;
Treacherous men | and murderers too,&lt;br&gt;
And workers of ill | with the wives of men;&lt;br&gt;
There Nithhogg sucked | the blood of the slain,&lt;br&gt;
And the wolf tore men; | would you know yet more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Völuspá 39&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Bellows 1923&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possibly the verb 𝘣𝘦𝘩𝘦𝘢𝘭𝘥𝘢ð means that nine adders occupy the running river of Hell, and that this steaming river is where all disease originates. This would certainly be implied by the Völuspá and Gylfaginning passages. Likewise in Ireland, the famous Salmon of Wisdom which swim the Boyne and the Shannon are &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/toddlectureserie10royauoft/page/292/mode/2up&#34;&gt;local reflexes&lt;/a&gt; of an earlier serpent-in-river myth; one theory, which I believe wholeheartedly, is that since Ireland has no natural snakes the salmon are a substitute of one scaly aquatic creature for another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In úair is abaig in cúas&lt;br&gt;
tuitit &#39;sin tiprait anúas:&lt;br&gt;
thís immarlethat ar lár,&lt;br&gt;
co nosethat na bratán.&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
When the cluster of [hazel] nuts is ripe&lt;br&gt;
they fall down into the well:&lt;br&gt;
they scatter below on the bottom,&lt;br&gt;
and the salmon eat them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metrical Dinshendchas - Sinann II&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Gwynn 1913&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if 𝘣𝘦𝘩𝘦𝘢𝘭𝘥𝘢ð instead meant that the serpents “behold” or “fear” the river, this also agrees with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.02.0137:book=29:chapter=12&#34;&gt;an account&lt;/a&gt; from Pliny about a Gaulish druidic rite wherein a druid steals a serpent’s egg, then as the creatures chase him he flees over a river, whereat the serpents halt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;there is another kind of egg, held in high renown by the people of the Gallic provinces, but totally omitted by the Greek writers. In summer time, numberless snakes become artificially entwined together, and form rings around their bodies with the viscous slime which exudes from their mouths, and with the foam secreted by them: the name given to this substance is “anguinum.” The Druids tell us, that the serpents eject these eggs into the air by their hissing,4 and that a person must be ready to catch them in a cloak, so as not to let them touch the ground; they say also that he must instantly take to flight on horseback, as the serpents will be sure to pursue him, until some intervening river has placed a barrier between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pliny&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Historia Naturalis 29.12&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve theorized on this passage &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/ogmios/status/1377785701983477769&#34;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, and since then have found a few other cognate myths. The simple meaning of the serpent’s fear of rivers, if the serpents represent disease, is an injunction to bathing in fresh water. The more hidden meaning may be one of attaining enlightenment. Recall how Asgard is supposedly separated from our world by a number of running rivers.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;See *Gylfaginning* 15, [here](https://www.germanicmythology.com/ProseEdda/BRODEURPrologeandGylfaginning.html).
&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Recall also that Thor must wade through those rivers to get to the home of the gods, while the others choose to ride on a flaming rainbow bridge above him.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;See *Gylfaginning* 15, [here](https://www.germanicmythology.com/ProseEdda/BRODEURPrologeandGylfaginning.html).
&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Perhaps this is Thor’s connection to humanity or his business killing devils which make him unclean, or perhaps he patrols the rivers for hidden dark spirits. Serpents are representative of bad spirits and sicknesses, which abhor fresh and clean running water, which can bite a sinner and either spread its own malignant essense into him, i.e. venom, or drink his blood thereby proving the sinner’s vile nature, i.e. a monster prefers blood like to itself. Thus passing over a river represents spiritual and corporeal purification, and the singer of this charm referencing a purifying river would indicate his own ritual purity, essential for healing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may be part of a larger Indo-European ritual cosmology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Nine-Herbs-Charm/Salmon.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Seofon-Worulde&#34;&gt;Seofon Worulde&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;ⵜFille and finule, felamihtigu twa&lt;br&gt;
þa ƿyrte gesceop ƿitig drihten&lt;br&gt;
halig on heofonum, þa he hongode&lt;br&gt;
sette and sænde on VII ƿorulde&lt;br&gt;
earmum and eadigum eallum to bote&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;br&gt;
ⵜFille and finule, a very mighty two,&lt;br&gt;
these worts the wise lord shaped,&lt;br&gt;
holy in the heavens, while he hung,&lt;br&gt;
set and sent them to VII worlds,&lt;br&gt;
poor and prosperous, as remedy for all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second esoteric passage in the Nine Herbs Charm is this one, not only for the Lord hanging in Heaven, but for the strange mention of “seven worlds” (𝘝𝘐𝘐 𝘸𝘰𝘳𝘶𝘭𝘥𝘦). Why not the typical nine worlds of the Eddas?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever seven worlds appear, you can be sure of ancient astrology. The seven worlds can be seen in the sky: the Sun, Moon, Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn. But then how can the Lord send Chervil and Fennel to those worlds? Who lives there? These seven worlds must then be places inhabited by creatures and accessible. Planets are not ruled out, but that concept would be foreign to the Anglo-Saxon mind. More likely these are separate regions of a larger cosmos, yet connected, much as the nine worlds of Yggdrasil are. Or they could be more abstract planes of being. In the Rig Veda there is an indication of both seven and nine worlds, but seven seems to prevail.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;See *The Cosmology of the Rigveda* by H. W. Wallis pg. 114, [here](https://archive.org/details/thecosmologyofth00walluoft/page/114/mode/2up), which concludes a cosmology of nine worlds by the time of Atharvaveda. For an argument for seven worlds, see *Vishnu in Rigveda* by Dmitri Semenov, [here](https://www.academia.edu/33047934/Vishnu_in_Rigveda), for certain passages which support the primacy of seven worlds in Rigveda.
&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There is Earth and Heaven firstly, which are joined together “like two bowls turned toward each other”. Then there is the midspace between them, bringing us to 3 locations. Then we divide the Earth and Heaven each into three subsections, bringing us to 7 locations in the cosmos. Each location is then governed by a planet in the sky, which is a god or a god’s abode, or in some senses his vehicle, since the gods preside in starry Heaven, much like the many halls enumerated in the Edda which belong to one or another Norse god.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these realms are not locations, rather they are states of being which can be traversed by the ritual practitioner.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; rel=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;hint--top hint--error hint--medium hint--rounded hint--bounce&#34; aria-label=&#34;See *Vishnu in Rigveda* by Semenov, [here](https://www.academia.edu/33047934/Vishnu_in_Rigveda).&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; How many times in the Rig Veda does the singer desire to attain Heaven, lifted up by Agni to the home of the gods? Too many to count. He achieves this through his ritual alteration of consciousness. This reference in the Nine Herbs Charm may be a distant echo of such a cosmology, with the healer who sings this chant altering his state of consciousness to better interact with the malignant spirits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some also have taken the word 𝘸𝘰𝘳𝘶𝘭𝘥𝘦 to mean “age of man” or “aion” instead or “world”, denoting time, not place. This would reduce the cosmology, but creates problems in parsing the logic of the verse then. Nevertheless, this has been the Nine Herbs Charm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will finish this article for now. This impressive example of ancient medicine splendidly treats the nine herbs as beings, warriors even, in a spiritual battle against plague wights which stalk the lands unfit for habitation, revealing an ancient animist perspective in addition to its Christian and Germanic pagan ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Nine-Herbs-Charm/Druid.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Druid with Herbs&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Chief Druid by Thomas Pennant, 1781&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;footnotelist&#34;&gt;&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style: none; padding-left: 0; margin-left: 40px&#34;&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;1.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;See Cotton MS Caligula A XV in the British Library, folio &lt;a href=&#34;https://iiif.bl.uk/uv/#?manifest=https://bl.digirati.io/iiif/ark:/81055/vdc_100058106204.0x000001&#34;&gt;123v&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://iiif.bl.uk/uv/#?manifest=https://bl.digirati.io/iiif/ark:/81055/vdc_100058106204.0x000001&#34;&gt;124r&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;2.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;See &lt;em&gt;Historia Brittonum&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gutenberg.org/files/1972/1972-h/1972-h.htm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the genealogy of English kings c. 850 AD, or the &lt;em&gt;Anglian Collection of Royal Genealogies&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/44510666&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; c. 800 AD.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;3.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;See &lt;em&gt;Gylfaginning&lt;/em&gt; 15, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.germanicmythology.com/ProseEdda/BRODEURPrologeandGylfaginning.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;4.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;See &lt;em&gt;The Cosmology of the Rigveda&lt;/em&gt; by H. W. Wallis pg. 114, &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/thecosmologyofth00walluoft/page/114/mode/2up&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, which concludes a cosmology of nine worlds by the time of Atharvaveda. For an argument for seven worlds, see &lt;em&gt;Vishnu in Rigveda&lt;/em&gt; by Dmitri Semenov, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/33047934/Vishnu_in_Rigveda&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for certain passages which support the primacy of seven worlds in Rigveda.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; padding-right: 10px; margin-left: -40px&#34;&gt;5.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display: inline-block; vertical-align: top; margin-left: 10px;&#34;&gt;See &lt;em&gt;Vishnu in Rigveda&lt;/em&gt; by Semenov, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/33047934/Vishnu_in_Rigveda&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; rev=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
        <category term="Religion" />
        <category term="Anglo-Saxon" />
        <category term="Magic" />
        <updated>2024-07-19T01:27:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/Milk-in-the-Orphic-Grave-Tablets/</id>
        <title>Milk in the Orphic Grave Tablets</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/Milk-in-the-Orphic-Grave-Tablets/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Milk-in-the-Orphic-Grave-Tablets/Milk-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;An Icelandic Landscape - Milk Flowing in Ginnungagap&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A post on the appearance of milk in the Orphic Grave Tablets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milk is used as a symbol of immortality, which an Orphic initiate attains after death through specific ritual. Numerous grave tablets have this analogy. Firstly, the Orphic grave tablets are a series of Greek inscriptions on gold tablets deposited in tombs, most often in Magna Grecia (South Italy). The greatest is the Petelia Tablet, seen here, which was rolled up inside a gold cylinder on a chain. Tablet is c. 300 BC, while the case is c. 100 AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Milk-in-the-Orphic-Grave-Tablets/Petelia-Tablet.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Petelia Tablet&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here you can see its Greek and next to it my translation. This is a rare tablet that does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mention milk, but which is the most famous and goes to show the kind of content we’re considering. After death the initiate is to find the Lake of Mnemosyne (Memory) and drink from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;bilingual-table&#34; style=&#34;color:rgb(201, 202, 204);&#34;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; Ancient Greek &lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt; English &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; Εὑρήσσειϛ δ’ Ἀίδαο δόμων ἐπ ἀριστερὰ κρήνην, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; You will find to the left of Hades&#39; halls a spring, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; πὰρ δ’ αὐτῆι λευκὴν ἑστηκυῖαν κυπάρισσον· &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; And beside it a shining cypress standing. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ταύτηϛ τῆϛ κρήνηϛ μηδὲ σχεδὸν ἐμπελάσειαϛ. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; You will not come near to this spring. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; εὑρήσειϛ δ’ ἑτέραν, τῆϛ Μνημοσύνηϛ ἀπὸ λίμνηϛ &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; You will find another, from the Lake of Memory, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ψυχρὸν ὕδωρ προρέον· φύλακεϛ δ’ ἐπίπροσθεν ἔασιν. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; cold water flowing. Guards are stationed before it. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; εἰπεῖν· Γῆϛ παῖϛ εἰμι καὶ Οὐρανοῦ ἀστερόεντοϛ, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Say: &#34;I am a child of Earth and starry Heaven, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; αὐτὰρ ἐμοὶ γένοϛ οὐράνιον· τόδε δ’ ἴστε καὶ αὐτοί. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; and my race is of heaven. You yourselves know this. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; δίψηι δ’ εἰμὶ αὔη καὶ ἀπόλλυμαι. ἀλλὰ δότ’ αἶψα &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; I am parched to thirst and dying. Give me, quickly, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ψυχρὸν ὕδωρ προρέον τῆϛ Μνημοσύνηϛ ἀπὸ λίμνηϛ.’ &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; the cold water flowing from the Lake of Memory.&#34; &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; καὐτοί σοι δώσουσι πιεῖν θείηϛ ἀπὸ κρήνηϛ, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; And they will give you to drink of the divine spring, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; καὶ τότ ἔπειτα τέλη σὺ μεθ’ ἡρώεσσιν ἀνάξειϛ. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; and then afterwards among the heroes you will have lordship. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; Μνημοσύνης τόδε ... ... ... θανεῖσθαι ... &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; ... of Memory ... ... ... to die ...  &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ... τόδε γραψ ... ... τογλωσειπα σκότοϛ ἀμφικαλύψαϛ. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; ... that is written ... ... darkness envelopes. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this the initiate will join the immortal heroes. Here is another one and my translation. This is a composition of the three Thurii Tablets A1-3 with almost identical texts; I have combined them in a way that seems most appropriate to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Milk-in-the-Orphic-Grave-Tablets/Thurii-Tablet.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A Thurii Tablet&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;bilingual-table&#34; style=&#34;color:rgb(201, 202, 204);&#34;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; Ancient Greek &lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt; English &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; Ἔρχομαι ἐκ καθαρῶν καθαρά, χθονίων βασίλεια, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; I come pure from the pure, Queen of the Underworld, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; Εὖκλε καὶ Εὐβουλεῦ τε καὶ θεοὶ ευδαίμονες ἄλλοι· &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Eukles, Euboleus, gods and other good spirits, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; καὶ γὰρ ἐγὼν ὑμῶν γένος εὔχομαι ὄλβιον εἶναι &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; for indeed of your blessed race I claim to be. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ποινὰν δ’ ἀνταπέτεισ’ αντ ἔργων οὔτι δικαίων. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; You have repaid unrighteous deeds with punishments. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; εἴτε με Μοῖρα ἐδάμασσε καὶ αθανατοι θεοι αλλοι &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; either Fate subdued me, or the other deathless gods, or the Thunderer throwing his thunderbolt. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; βροντε τ’ ἀστεροπε τε και αιθαλοεντι κεραυνῶ. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; I flew out of the bitter grief-stricken circle, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; Κύκλου δ’ εξεπταν βαρυπενθοες αργαλεοιο &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; to the desired crown I came with swift feet, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ’Ιμερτόν δ’ επεβαν στεφανον ποσι καρπαλιμοισι &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; I went down under the bosom of the Lady, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; Δεσποινας δ’ ύπο κολπον εδυν χθονιας βασιλειασ. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Queen of the Underworld. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; Νυν δ’ ικετης αγνην ηκω παρα Φερσεφονειαν &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Now a supplicant I have come beside pure Persephone &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ’Ως με προφρων πεμψη εδρας ες τας μακαριστας εὐαγέων &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; so that, in kindness, she will send me to the seats of the most blessed pious ones. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ’Ολβιε και μακαριστε, θεος δέση άντι &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Happy and most blessed, a god you shall be instead of a mortal. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; βροτοιο εριφοσ ες γαλ’ επετον. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; A kid goat flying into milk. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Notice the last line, “a kid (goat) flying/rushing into milk,” immediately after becoming a Θεός. An allegory for apotheosis, in which the young goat is submerged in that which he craves most, in the same way the initiate entering the halls of the heroes is plunged into bliss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my translation of a third tablet from Thurii, Italy, known as A4. We once again see the formulation of a kid goat falling or rushing into milk immediately after the initiate has become a god, Θεός.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;bilingual-table&#34; style=&#34;color:rgb(201, 202, 204);&#34;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; Ancient Greek &lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt; English &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; Ἀλλ’ ὁπόταν ψυχὴ προλίπηι φάος ἀελίοιο, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Whenever the soul might leave behind the light of the Sun, &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; δεξιὸν εννοιας δει τινα πεφυλαγμένον εὖ μάλα πάντα· &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; travel to the right, being well guarded in every way. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; χαῖρε παθὼν τὸ πάθημα τὸδ’ οὔπω πρόσθε ἐπεπόνθεις· &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Hail, you who has experienced this experience, which you had not experienced before. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; θεὸς ει ελεεινού έξ άνθρόπου. ἔριφος ἐς γάλα ἔπετες. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; A god has been gained from a man. A young goat falling into milk. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; χαῖρε χαῖρε· δεξιὰν ὁδοιπορών &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Hail, hail. Journey to the right through &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; λειμῶνάς τε ἱεροὺς κατ’ ἄλσεα Φερσεφονείας. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; the holy meadows and groves of Persephone. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a fourth from Pelinna, Thessaly, Greece. Here you see it most strongly, because it’s repeated three times (almost as if reflecting the thrice-blessed τρισολβιε appellation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;bilingual-table&#34; style=&#34;color:rgb(201, 202, 204);&#34;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; Ancient Greek &lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt; English &lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; νῦν ἔθανες καὶ νῦν ἐγένου, τρισόλβιε, ἄματι τῶιδε. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Now you have died and you have been born, thrice-blessed, on this very day. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; εἰπεῖν Φερσεφόναι σ’ ὅτι Βάκχιος αὐτὸς ἔλυσε. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Tell Persephone that Bacchus himself freed you. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; ταιῦρος εἰς γάλα ἔθορες. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; A bull into milk, you leapt. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; αἶψα εἰς γάλα ἔθορες. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; Quickly into milk, you sprang. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; κριὸς εἰς γάλα ἔπεσες. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; A ram into milk, you fell. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; οἶνον ἔχεις εὐδαίμονα τιμὴν &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; You have wine as a fortunate honor &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; καὶ σὺ μὲν εἶς ὑπὸ γῆν τελέσας ἅπερ ὄλβιοι ἄλλοι &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; and you, indeed, will go under the earth, having been consecrated &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;  &lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt; as the other blessed ones. &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why milk? The simplest anthropological reading is that milk is something a kid (goat) craves, so falling into (an ocean of) milk represents the good afterlife, one where all the things which we sought in the  material world are supplied in abundance. This imagery would make sense to a pastoral people. This summing up all of Orphic initiation into a single symbolic phrase is called a &lt;em&gt;synthema&lt;/em&gt;, and would serve to remind the initiate that all his trainings are what earn him immortality or knowledge of his true self. But the verb “rushing or leaping” (&lt;em&gt;εθορες&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;επεσες&lt;/em&gt;) could also imply a ritualistic action or dance performed before death. We see this in other Greek cults, as when Cretan youths imitated the dance of the &lt;em&gt;Kouretes&lt;/em&gt;, or when “rushing” Maenads celebrate the coming of Dionysus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Milk-in-the-Orphic-Grave-Tablets/Taurus-Leap.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cretan Athletes Leaping Over a Bull&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milk in Greece, as in all Aryan societies, was connected intimately with the stars and therefore Heaven &amp;amp; the gods. The word for milk, &lt;em&gt;γάλα&lt;/em&gt; “gala”, seemed to converge with celestial words, like the Milky Way galaxy, known as &lt;em&gt;γάλακτος&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;κύκλος&lt;/em&gt; “milky wheel”, &lt;em&gt;γαλαχιος&lt;/em&gt; “galaxios”, or even &lt;em&gt;το γάλα&lt;/em&gt; “the milk”. The Milky Way was the Road of Souls to the afterlife, possibly what Pindar called “Zeus’s Way” in Olympian 2. Souls would also descend from the abode of the blessed gods to incarnate, thus explaining why babies needed to drink specifically milk from their mothers. There were many beliefs that souls became stars once in Heaven, as in this Arkesine inscription “Mother, do not weep for me. What is the use? You ought rather to reverence me, for I have become an evening star, among the gods.” So then our milk seems to be a stand-in for Heaven, or that the Heavens were observably full of milk. And when the tablets say &lt;em&gt;εις γάλα εθορες&lt;/em&gt;, it may not mean “you rushed into milk”, but “you rushed into the galaxy (i.e. Heaven &amp;amp; the gods)”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milk was symbolic of the end of life for blessed heroes and initiates, and of the beginning of life for newborn babies. Thus it probably represented a cycle of rebirth, or at least incarnation. The wicked are deprived of milk in Hades or Tartaros. Is this idea Indo-European? We see an identical conflation in Ireland, where the Irish name of the Milky Way is the &lt;em&gt;Bealach ná Bó Finne&lt;/em&gt; or “Way of the White Cow”; Vedic Aryans called it, among other names, &lt;em&gt;devapatha&lt;/em&gt; or “god path”. In each, the souls of dead heroes walk it. The primordial milk-giving cow in &lt;em&gt;Gylfaginning&lt;/em&gt; supports the life of Ymir, and perhaps the Norse thought it was her milk which spilled across Heaven to form the Milky Way. In Irish we seem to have a heavenly cow as well in the &lt;em&gt;Bó Firinne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The connection between milk and the white galaxy overhead is strong, as is the conception of that region of the sky being the home of the gods. These are the double-meanings which Greek Orphic initiates understood when going through their trainings. For the initiate, his recollection of his “true self” would earn him entry into the abode of the gods and heroes, and so would literally enter the milk above, and fall into a milk which is desirable and pleasant. Since his enlightened state is due to his initiation, we could even say that his initiation on Earth is an early development of his enlightened state in Heaven, and so his initiation is the milk he seeks. And the initiate would be the young goat, inexperienced and even clumsy, who needs spiritual sustenance (i.e. Orphic wisdom).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the milk formulae in these tablets appear to be synthemata meant to remind the initiate of the culmination of his Orphic training, and simultaneously of the immense pleasures of Heaven and the gods after death, just as we take pleasure from drinking fresh milk on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s my broad, surface level theory, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fin.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="Religion" />
        <category term="Orphism" />
        <category term="Greek" />
        <updated>2024-05-18T09:47:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/Beowulf-and-the-Tain-Bo-Fraich/</id>
        <title>Beowulf and the Táin Bó Fraích</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/Beowulf-and-the-Tain-Bo-Fraich/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Beowulf-and-the-Tain-Bo-Fraich/Beowulf-and-the-Dragon-John-Howe.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Beowulf and the Dragon by John Howe&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beowulf is, of course, the primeval myth of the Anglo-Saxons. It takes place in Denmark, but it may have a broader North European origin. But it has little-known similarities to the Irish saga known as the &lt;em&gt;Táin Bó Fraích&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt; story is set in Scandinavia in the 6th century AD, but the manuscript its written on was produced around the year 1000 AD. It’s still contentious how old the story really is, when it was first recorded, and whether it was originally an oral tale or a written composition. &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt; is also an extremely strange story. It is thematically and imagistically Germanic pagan, but the story is Christian, which has led some scholars to conclude it was not a &lt;em&gt;scop&lt;/em&gt; who wrote the story, but a monk in a monastery. &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt; also seems original in the world of Germanic sagas, it is unlike any other story. Who is Grendel, why does Beowulf wrestle him naked and tear his arm off? Why fight Grendel’s mother underwater? How does the dragonslaying episode at the end fit in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recap of Beowulf and a comparison to the &lt;em&gt;Táin Bó Fraích&lt;/em&gt;: Beowulf appears from far away, and a watchman remarks: “Never have I seen a greater noble warrior upon the earth, than that one of your number, a man in his war-weaving”. In the Irish saga, Fraech and his retinue of the &lt;em&gt;Síde&lt;/em&gt; mound are spotted from afar:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The watchman sees them from the dun when they had come into the plain of Cruachan. “A multitude I see,” he says, “(come) towards the dun in their numbers. Since Ailill and Maev assumed sovereignty there came not to them before, and there shall not come to them, a multitude, which is more beautiful, or which is more splendid.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beowulf approaches Hrothgar’s hall and is greeted by a herald before meeting the Earl. The herald returns with permission to enter the hall and feast. In the &lt;em&gt;Táin&lt;/em&gt;, Fraech sits outside &lt;em&gt;Dún Chrúachan&lt;/em&gt; until he is received by a retainer, who eventually grants him the King’s welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They alight in front of the dun. They tent their steeds, and they loose the chase-hounds… A message comes from the king for a parley with them. It is asked whence they came, they name themselves according to their true names, “Fraech, son of Idath this,” say they. The steward tells it to the king and queen. “Welcome to them,” say Ailill and Medb; “It is a noble youth who is there,” says Ailill, “let him come into the Liss (outer court).” The fourth of the house is allotted to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside, the warriors feast and are served by the queen out of a jeweled cup. Someone relates the hero’s skill at swimming. The Grendel episode is unique to Beowulf, but the fight against Grendel’s mother overlaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Beowulf-and-the-Tain-Bo-Fraich/Beowulf-and-Grendel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Beowulf and Grendel&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Beowulf&lt;/em&gt;, he dives into the dark pool, and swims downward until the water monster, Grendel’s mother, grabs him by the side. He wrestles at first, before finding a sword in her lair and beheading her with it. He beheads Grendel’s body as well, and carries the head back to land. In the &lt;em&gt;Táin&lt;/em&gt;, Fraech is swimming in a black lake as Aillil and Medb look on when he is attacked by a water beast, who grabs him by the side. He wrestles the monster, before crying out for a sword from the crowd watching him. Aillil’s daughter Findabair swims out to him with a sword. Fraech beheads the monster, and carries its head back to land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a final episode in both tales far away from their previous settings, when Beowulf kills a dragon and Fraech battles a serpent, each with the help of a single companion, Wiglaf and Conall Cernach respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![Beowulf Against the Dragon after a Drawing by Walter Zweigler, 1896](/Beowulf-and-the-Tain-Bo-Fraich/Beowulf-Against-the-Dragon.jpg) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are numerous other smaller similarities you could find in your reading of both. And yet the stories don’t align exactly either. Beowulf appears to fight Grendel, Fraech appears to woo the princess Findabair. There is no cognate of Grendel in the &lt;em&gt;Táin Bó Fráech&lt;/em&gt;. Beowulf has a personal history of great deeds which is not shared by Fraech in this tale. Hrothgar is attacked by Grendel and his mother, while Fraech’s monster is a trap laid by Aillil and Medb to stop him from eloping with the princess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories have many differences, but we still cannot deny that many images and themes are the same in both, beyond what is reasonable for two unrelated legends. Is this Irish influence in Anglo-Saxon society? Some academics have tried to “monasticize” Beowulf, because if it could be proved that Beowulf was written in a monastery, we could conclude that the Táin Bó Fráech was used as a model for Beowulf. We could imagine some young Anglo-Saxon monk studying under his Irish peers and learning their legends, perhaps learning Gaelic, and craving to see his own race represented in such a heroic light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ![The Roman Monk by Alexander Cabanel](/Beowulf-and-the-Tain-Bo-Fraich/The-Roman-Monk-by-Alexander-Cabanel.jpg) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t believe this monastic theory. Academics debate it because there’s positive evidence from this period, and academics hate speculation. There is equal evidence in support of an North European dragon slaying hero myth, represented in Beowulf, Fraech, Siegfried, and ultimately Apollo. We could easily say that Fraech and Beowulf are relfexes of popular gods, like Apollo slaying Python. Aillil and Medb are quite clearly the solar and lunar deities of the Irish pantheon. But Beowulf is tied to non-mythical history. The characters and clans named there are real. The characters in Beowulf tie him to 6th century Scandinavia. Now we must ask, how much of Beowulf is myth? Was Beowulf a real person who had a myth applied over his life story? Was Grendel real? Or was this originally a myth that was laid on top of the local geography? Many Irish stories which purport to be historical share extreme similarities with the myths of other cultures. Likely among Northern Europeans, myth and history were united. After all, the post-Classical idea of a “myth” as something separate from history is certainly not native. But these are questions which neither I nor scholars can answer. If any of you have ideas on this, please share, and if any of you do some reading and find some detail which sheds light on our ancient stories, share that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fin.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="Irish Myth" />
        <updated>2023-09-18T04:18:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/You-Have-Become-a-Wolf/</id>
        <title>You Have Become a Wolf</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/You-Have-Become-a-Wolf/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/You-Have-Become-a-Wolf/Wolf-Warriors.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Two Ulfhednar Warriors&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Hittite law code confirms the Indo-European wolf-warrior tradition of young men leaving society to dress as animals while plundering their neighbors. A discussion on this Hittite source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source for today is the essay “The Meaning of the Expression ‘To Become a Wolf’ in Hittite” by Jos Weitenberg, in the book &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/pearson-ed.-perspectives-on-indo-european-language-culture-and-religion-2-vols.-1991/page/189/mode/1up&#34;&gt;Perspectives on Indo-European Language, Culture, and Religion&lt;/a&gt;. The author speaks in academese and tries to avoid drawing any connection to the broader Indo-European world, specifically in reference to the &lt;em&gt;Koryos&lt;/em&gt; band. This is a warband of young men who were ritualistically cast out from polite society, and sent to the wilderness to hunt animals and raid their neighboring tribes. This went on for some years until the boys became men, after which the men would destroy the rags they had worn as clothes and rejoin society through a ritual and sacrifice, usually at the summer solstice. While in &lt;em&gt;koryos&lt;/em&gt;, these young men were &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; members of society and did not have legal rights, so no claims could be made for their deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why it has intrigued Hittitologists that one law code contains the phrase “You have become a wolf” in a section on murder and abduction, specifically it says that if a man abducts a married woman (with intent to keep her as his own), and if he brings along friends to help in the abduction, and anyone dies in the process, the killer does not have to pay &lt;em&gt;weregild&lt;/em&gt; for the death. That is to say, the killing is justified and not murder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tak-ku SAL-na-an ku-iš-ki pít-ti-nu-uz-zi nu-ku-i-e-eš a-ap-pa-an-an-da pa-a-an-zi tak-ku LÚ-MEŠ na-aš-ma LÚ-MEŠ ak-kán-zi šar-ni-ik-zi-i NÚ-GÁL zi-ik-wa UR-BAR-RA-as ki-iš-ta-at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone abducts a woman and if those who go after, three persons or two persons, are killed there will be no compensation. ‘You have become a wolf.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly no compensation is needed when the killed men were in the act of abducting the man’s wife. To pay the abductor’s family would be absurd. This is beyond the usual disagreement or honor killing. In fact, these actions which violate law and order are exactly what disqualify the abductor from demanding his legal death-price. His rights become forfeit when he acts against justice. Symbolically, be has cast himself out of justice, like young men in &lt;em&gt;koryos&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the men who abduct a woman may not be ritualistically and permanently cast out of society, but in this instance they are denied their rights due to their feral actions. And so a judge proclaims to them “you have become wolves” to strip them of those rights. We find this expression again in a royal decree of Hattusili I when he disowns his son:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DUMU-mis NU-DUMU-as. amminzan-a ÌR-MEŠ-amman UR-BAR-RA-as mān pankur-set I-EN ēstu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My son is a non-son. But let him be one of you, my servants, like the kin of the wolf”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this phrase has become a more general saying, signifying a degradation of rights and standing in society. And we see similar sayings in other Indo-European societies. In Greek one becomes a wolf by eating human remains during a sacrifice, then that person is born a wolf (&lt;em&gt;λύκοι γενέσθαι&lt;/em&gt;). There is an Old Icelandic oath which unites enemies as relatives, and says that if one breaks the oath, he “will become a wolf and will be persecuted in all places where people hunt wolves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the Frankish Salic Law, banishment is expressed with the phrase “wargus sit” or “let him become a wolf”. Even in Old Armenian there is a Christian marriage law tract by Bishop Sewantos which states that premarital relations cause a man to “become a wolf” (gayl ełew). If you look, you can find more examples in each branch of the Indo-European tree. But here in Hittite we find it the oldest, and yet the wolf saying has already become abstracted by their time, showing that the &lt;em&gt;koryos&lt;/em&gt; war band is older than Hittite by far. Whether a man was part of the tribe, or if he was outcast, was a major consideration in those days. We know from Brehon and Vedic law that the law was something which could only be leveraged by members of the community in good standing in order to resolve conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/You-Have-Become-a-Wolf/Hittite-Scenery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A scene from prehistoric Europe, by Andre Houot&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="Hittite" />
        <updated>2023-08-26T11:42:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/Gardens/</id>
        <title>Gardens</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/Gardens/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Pasted-image-20250201125302.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A post on gardens. The eternal repose of the aristocratic soul, his garden, it can be done very well or very poorly. Some are outright terrible. They are a deep European tradition, archetypal (Eden, Hersperides, Gethsemane, Elysium). The contrast between the controlled nature inside the garden walls and the wild nature outside called back to the garden at Humanity’s beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;French gardens are the most well known globally, for good reason. The Frenchmen had just about perfected the art. The formula: a medieval château encircled by cultivated greenery. The &lt;em&gt;jardin á la française&lt;/em&gt; as a style developed from the earlier Italian Renaissance garden. This Italian style began with walled urban gardens used to grow specific herbs, flowers, and vegetables like grapes for wine. As the Renaissance began and Classical ideas drifted through the air, people picked up tomes of Pliny, Varro, and Ovid, who reminded then of the &lt;strong&gt;splendor&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;glory&lt;/strong&gt; of the gardens surrounding Roman Villas. The Renaissance Italians desperately wanted to revive this style, to resurrect a piece of Rome’s legacy. They developed these walled gardens as well as open ones, geometrically planned and filled with beautiful decoration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Pasted-image-20250201125351.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Italians didn’t draw solely from Rome, and a garden is not simply a place to store plants and art. Medieval monks had cultivated the practice of gardening in their monasteries. Monks &lt;strong&gt;demanded&lt;/strong&gt; order and peace for silent meditation and effective prayer to God. This ideal of a garden, both splendorous and tranquil, both sprawling and controlled, is the impetus for the aristocratic adoption of the art of gardening in Europe and now in all the world. Taken from the glory of Rome and the dedication of Christian monks. Outside the city walls was dangerous nature: brutal, elemental, and obeying the law of the jungle. Inside Man’s garden, nature was controlled, shepherded, and led towards perfection, as in Eden. The garden planner imitated the Lord, ordering the world from disarray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Pasted-image-20250201125453.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, gardeners often made use of mathematics to appeal to the human senses. Their gardens were planned with geometric forms and placed high above the city by his villa. Nature bounded by mathematical order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Ambrogiana_utens.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Ambrogiana Utens&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times the geometry could be too much and begin to stifle the natural beauty of the garden plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Giardino-di-Boboli.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Giardino di Boboli&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not all gardens developed in this rigid way. Often it was simply a walled or restricted area where rare trees could grow, flowers bloom, a place for walking and contemplating. This is the incredibly large garden at &lt;em&gt;Château dela Reine&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Chateau-dela-Reine.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These styles were quickly adopted in France, as when King Charles VIII found them in Napoli. Every French aristocrat soon dreamt the dream of Nature cultivated by Man. To that end, the French did not keep their gardens strictly walled, but imposed order on larger sweeps of land. The French loved to impose geometry on their gardens. And the garden as a whole was an ambulatory for the King or Nobleman, to clear his mind and refresh his spirit. The French aim: to cultivate those qualities in men which led to the power of Rome, of Medieval Christendom, and to the power of France; to be overcome with Nature, to learn from it; to sharpen himself on Nature, to master it, and to rule it lovingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Pasted-image-20250201125831.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gardens at Versaille are the most renowned. They entertained hundreds of guests on a daily basis after King Louis XIV moved his court there. But this is where gardens can suffer under their own weight. The overly mathematical nature of many gardens of the French style can prevent the very goal they set out to achieve. Nature cannot exist in strictly geometrical forms, neatly trimmed, the landscape has its own features which accentuate its beauty and which the garden should emphasize. When the straight path cuts through the trees, however, any natural features are disregarded in favor of hueman convenience or sloth. This is one feature that the English country garden avoids. When designs become overly mathematical, some can have more sinister meanings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Pasted-image-20250201125919.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Pasted-image-20250201125937.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The English, naturally, adopted the art of gardening in turn. Unlike the Italian garden of potted plants and marble statues, or the French garden of numerical purity and direct walking paths, the English garden appears as an overgrown flower bed, a home for insects and plants. This tight infilling of beautiful flora is balanced by the wide area of cut lawn. It gives the aristocratic man a place to walk, a place to run or ride horseback, a place to admire Nature’s flourishing, and a place to meditate surrounded by life. Of all the garden traditions so far, this one appears the most vitalist, almost overrun with life, yet tranquil. One could spend all day in leisure in the English garden, both controlled and wild, thinking, meditating, watching the birds or butterflies before reentering the world of struggle and fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Chenies-Manor-House.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chenies Manor House&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This style of lawns which stretch for miles in the English Country Garden. It spread to many places, especially in Germany, and is iconic to the English manor house. But even if the English garden isn’t enjoyed by Man, its focus on Nature above marble statuary or geometry means that it is at all times appreciated by Harmony itself. It needs no inhabitant to be beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Stowe-Park-Buckinghamshire.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Stowe Park Buckinghamshire&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes to show the popularity of these gardens that even men of modest means apportioned their property to these purposes. You didn’t need an estate house to plant flowers in the yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Pasted-image-20250201130243.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The largest estates, however, often mixed the worst of the French and English styles, setting out endless mowed lawns alongside neatly trimmed bushes. Nowhere for life to thrive, purely decorative and meant only to be seen from afar from the windows of the manor house. I like this style very little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Pasted-image-20250201130311.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Wrest Park Bedfordshire&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A demonstration of the different tastes of the Italian, French, and English nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/Italian-Example.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Giardino Giusti&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/French-Example.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jardin du Luxembourg&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/Gardens/English-Example.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chiltern Estate&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fin.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <updated>2022-07-07T05:41:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/Civitas/</id>
        <title>Civitas</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/Civitas/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Civitas/Gondolin.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Gondolin by spartank42 on DevianArt&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chinese have always lived in houses, yes, if that’s all you mean by ‘civilization’… Everything for oneself, everything for personal utility: a pleasure in cruelty toward the weak and toward animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bronze Age Pervert&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People argue over civilization without first understanding what they speak of. I wonder if some modern nations have ever truly had civilization, but it might be better to ask if we have it presently. Our word “civilization” descends from the Latin “civitas”, and its meaning hasn’t drifted far. The common understanding is that a “civilized” society is non-hostile to its neighbors or to strangers, it is productive, introspective, and cohesive among its members. It produces and enjoys culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Roman idea of civitas is not much different on the surface, but utterly foreign underneath. To the early Romans, the world was hostile. In their early years, every summer a different neighbor launched a raid against their city, usually from loosely organized hill-tribes. These hill-tribes are not civilizations, not cities, and do not cultivate civitas. Sometimes it’s not hill-tribes but Gaulish war bands that come raiding, nevertheless, the countryside was full of danger from mobile bands of young warriors wanting to raid and kill. This behavior is Indo-European, but it is not civilized. When these roving tribes did settle, it was in familial arrangements, villages so small that everyone was related. Some parts of Europe and western America may still know this type of settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Romans conquered the Aequi tribe, for instance, their settlements were so small they didn’t even warrant naming. In the Aeneid, Virgil calls the Aequi “a nation of rude mountaineers, addicted to the chase and to predatory habits, by which they sought to supply the deficiencies of their rugged and barren soil.” These were hunter-gatherers in the Italian Apennine Mountains. Rome subjugated the Aequi and caused them to exit their family homesteads (some may say, their longhouses) to form larger settlements, which became cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might call the Aequi “civilized”, but can you impose the virtue of Civitas onto another people? Authentic civitas must rise from within. Civitas is that virtue which causes cities to rise from villages of their own accord. The Aequi familial homesteads were bound together by family ties, not by civitas. Likewise sprawling modern cities aren’t held together by civitas, but by economic convenience. People move in and float away as money demands, without loyalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The civic state, by contrast, isn’t held together by blood or money but by the ideal of a society. The powerful families of the familial villages coalesce to form a larger civil society, founded on a common dream or ideal. A Romulus figure appears to inspire a common aspiration into them. The underclasses follow suit. We see that first the aristocratic classes form the idea of a city, and thus birth the city’s daemon, it’s over-spirit; then the city begins to live, populated by lesser men who cannot follow a vision as well as the aristocrats might.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Athens was ruled by the &lt;em&gt;Eupatridae&lt;/em&gt;, powerful men who kept the city alive in its spirit, grew its economy, and led wars to defend it. Utterly loyal to the place they ruled through their civitas (or άρετέ). Later these became the &lt;em&gt;Pentekosiomidemnoi&lt;/em&gt;, which fulfilled the same role. This old aristocracy was formed as a league of powerful military men who would lead the city with personal care and attention to its virtue and citizenry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aristocratic man’s willingness to uphold the city and its ideal is the first sign of civitas. The city isn’t formed around convenience, or led passively, slowly, and receptively; its purpose is to fulfill a dream and therefore must be active, swift, and powerful. These virtues are only characteristic of the most virtuous men of the society, never of its underclasses. But the underclasses become charged with the same energy and purpose as is put forward by their leadership, and thereby improve themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many cities in the ancient world and even more in the modern world are bereft of civic spirit at all. No virtuous leaders, and so no virtuous populace. Entire nations go without civitas and have no true cities. Urban housing becomes mere slave quarters for global finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are two opposing ends of the civilizational cycle. On the one end is the most basic family structure, the homestead or longhouse. On the other end is the overdeveloped metropolis. The metropolis occurs once the power struggles between small cities are ended, and a single larger state becomes dominant. Just as family ideals are subsumed into the city-state, civic ideals are subsumed into the nation or empire, and usually a secretive class of oligarchs, lacking courage or loyalty, dominates. Civitas is overtaken by patriotism, or by some other more generalized virtue showing adherence to symbols only. The countryside is made safe by the state’s power, and the affairs of the state become too large for a single man to effectively engage in. Men can understand a city and care for a city, but the benefits which one receives through civic care are diminished as the city’s influence grows. The city is no longer the sole interest of the men who live in it; it becomes the interest of everyone under its power as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take Rome as an example: the streets had filled with the poor who were forced from the countryside, who had no virtue and wanted only bread. The nobles who once would fight against the city’s decay could move to their villas in Campania. Poor living conditions in Rome and the homogenization of neighboring cities meant that the upper artisanal classes and merchants could move to other Italian cities with minimal difficulty. In the end, no one was left to care for Rome herself, and the only interests left were those of personal gain. Most often this personal wealth was acquired by using Rome as a skinsuit, pretending that there still was a Rome when her people had abandoned her or when German barbarians moved in. Perhaps the economy kept growing, but Civilization had ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in late Rome, we live in a metropolis which is deprived of personality in favor of function. The people who live in the city are deprioritized in favor of the more wealthy people who travel or commute to the city from outside. As I said, the city becomes a skinsuit for outsiders. The city is no longer a place in itself, with beauty and identity, but only a hub for economic convenience. Likewise, the economic wheels require slaves to work them, and now everywhere we see newly-made highrise apartments where high-salaried tech workers and diversity officers can waste money living the fake glamor of the “urban lifestyle.” This genre of housing which fills most modern cities can only be called slave quarters for the minions of the economic rulers of our fallen cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Civitas is what makes a wattle and daub village into a city, then we have almost no cities left. They’ve been gutted. Even if men had civitas blazing in their hearts, what cities are left to care for or participate in? Globalism is a crusade against this very feeling. If we want cities and civitas to return, we can’t revive it from what we have now. There aren’t even family villages to act as the seeds of a city. So, we must create them. Civitas demands regard and respect for the forebears of the city and its ancestors. At some point, we must become the men whom our descendants will honor. Ancient families enshrined their forebears as household spirits so as to never neglect them or their ideals. How to achieve this? BAP tells us our instincts for piracy and warbands will rise again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginnings of a family village, one which can cultivate a noble line and act as the estate of the &lt;em&gt;pater familias&lt;/em&gt;, lie in the leader of the war band claiming land for his own and destroying his enemies. We can find suitable places for this in the less civilized parts of the earth. The civilized parts are merely domesticated now. You must see this, because nowhere is there civitas among the people. Not true civitas, but only its echo, the afterimage of goodwill towards neighbors but never the will to go to war for your city against others. This lack of feeling is a historical aberration which won’t last forever. A day will come when civitas returns to the far reaches of the Western world, if not due to visionary men, then due to the necessity against enemies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to the greatest point on the nature of the civic virtue: the core unit of civitas, without which it cannot function, is friendship between men. This is what binds the Indo-European &lt;em&gt;kóryos&lt;/em&gt; as well as the city-state. It is another reason men have come under attack today. A city inhabited by men who feel loyalty to each other and to their city is much harder to manipulate than a city of atomized individuals. The training of the city’s young boys was of the utmost importance, and every city of note in the Classical and Christian eras alike instituted rituals to initiate their boys into patriotic manhood. This is the purpose of the famous Spartan agoge, for instance. The great bureaucracies of today want men without friends, without a permanent home, without roots, and without the courage to fight. If the Greeks could see modern men, who allow their cities to be uprooted, humiliated, and defiled without consequences, they would be filled with existential grief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the virtues in life tie into one another. Loyalty, friendship, and civitas stand side by side. When you cultivate one, you encourage the others. Therefore if we want to see the rise of new and powerful cities, we must first show loyalty to friends, and courage towards our ideal. You are the city. Without this, the world will remain an undifferentiated grey mass.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <updated>2022-06-28T17:46:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/AmericanGenetics/</id>
        <title>American Genetics</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/AmericanGenetics/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;The-Genetic-Makeup-of-the-Great-American-Race&#34;&gt;The Genetic Makeup of the Great American Race&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/Boones-First-View-of-Kentucky-William-Renney.jpg&#34; class=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;TLDR&#34;&gt;TLDR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The average modern American has an admixture that is roughly 40% British/English, 20% Irish, 25% broadly West European (N French and W German), and 10% Scandinavian. There are many ethnic enclaves throughout the country who break from this pattern, including Amish, Irish, Mennonite, Mormon, Arcadian/Cajun, Nuevos Mexicanos, and Appalachians. White Americans, on average, have almost no non-White admixture, including from Jewish, African, or Asian sources.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, “American” is a race, or rather, a family of smaller races which find their origins among Enagland and Wales, Scotland, Ireland, France, Germany, Denmark, and Norway. There are other populations in the United States today, but I will be focusing on the American race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the earliest times, the American race has been a mirror of Western and Northern Europe in the New World. A proposed seal for the United States, drawn in 1776 by Pierre du Simitière, is shown below, which shows the six nations which were taken as the origin of the colonial American population: England (and Wales), Scotland, Ireland, France, Holland, and Germany. As we will see, this characterization is accurate. Some people will try to convince you that America was an Anglo-Saxon ethnostate before Germans, Irish, and Italians moved in. This is not true. Britain has, however, always been the largest substrate for most of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The genetics paper this article is drawing data from is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms14238&#34;&gt;“Clustering of 770,000 genomes reveals post-colonial population structure of North America”&lt;/a&gt; by Han et al, published in Nature on Feb 7, 2017. These researchers took 769,444 DNA samples from &lt;a href=&#34;http://Ancestry.com&#34;&gt;Ancestry.com&lt;/a&gt; data; 96% of the people sampled had ancestors who were born within the US. From this dataset, we get a canvas showing the large swaths of White American population movement surrounded by a smattering of niche genetic groups across the continent, including Caribbeans, Acadians, and Mexicans. On &lt;a href=&#34;http://Ancestry.com&#34;&gt;Ancestry.com&lt;/a&gt;, you can also set your ‘pedigree’, or the locations your ancestors were born. This is a great help, because we can now identify the movement of people over time, not simply where they are now. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All data and figures in this writeup come from this paper or its supplementary material.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; Most samples are from California, followed by New York and Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmY0KDWUAIHqqs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Sample Origins by State&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Number of DNA samples with reported birth locations in US states. These numbers are obtained from pedigree nodes linked to DNA samples. Note that the counts by US state don&#39;t add up to the total number of US born samples because &#34;US born&#34; also includes Puerto Rico, Guam and other US territories.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study traces ‘identity-by-descent’ (IBD) data to create their genetic clusters. An IBD analysis tracks DNA segments that are not merely similar, but are descended from the same ancestor. This is a sample of how clusters are calculated across individuals in this sizeable dataset. This method works best for populations that are not relatively diverse and in which one segment of the genome can occur within numerous participants, which would show descent from a common ancestor within recent generations. Testing between two random Americans is not ideal, since for the last few centuries barriers to mating have been very low, but this dataset overcomes this through its sheer size, and the researchers are able to perform this analysis nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmaGd7XoAIdBmm.png&#34; alt=&#34;IBD Diagram&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Pedigree, recombination and resulting IBD segments, schematic representation.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;!-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Genetic-Affinities&#34;&gt;Genetic Affinities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First let’s inspect the genetic affinities between groups, starting with the PCA distribution. Below we see participants grouped into states and mapped based on genetic similarity. For the non-initiated, distance in this graphic roughly represents total genetic distance between populations. You can see that California, New York, and Texas are largest, followed by PA, MI, and IL, etc. The far Northeast and the Deep South both form highly differentiated clusters (ethnostates?) forming two ends of the spectrum. The Mid-Atlantic and Upper South cluster closer to the West of the country. We can already see historic movements: notice that Utah is close to New York, a remnant of Mormonism’s origins in upstate NY before moving out west. See how the French of Louisiana drag their state towards the French Canadians of New England. These clusters will color all future maps in this paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmauz2WYAAlP7T.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;PCA Chart&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&#34;Principal components (PCs) are computed using kernel PCA, in which the kernel matrix is defined by total IBD between pairs of states, normalized to remove the effect of variation in within-state IBD. US states that share high levels of IBD on average are placed closer to each other in the projection onto the first two principal components. The area of each circle is scaled by number of self-reported birth locations in the state (Supplementary Fig. 1). US states are coloured by geographic region (Northeast, South, Midwest and West).&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary map is below, the one which merits reposting again and again. The DNA data clusters into the groups shown above, which are then color-coded here based on genetic similarity only, not geographic origin. Those groups are the American sub-races. But what does this graphic show? There are three things going on with each dot: color, size, and location. The dot does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; represent a participant in this study, but rather the participant’s parents or other ancestors. Each dot’s location show the participant’s &lt;em&gt;parent’s&lt;/em&gt; birthplace. Size indicates the number of birth locations reported for that area. Color represents the nearest genetic cluster which participants from that area associate with. So if you’re DNA clustered with the blue datapoints, you would likely be from Pennsylvania, if yellow, likely from the coastal South. Also, dots are only counted when their OR is above a threshold value, giving the appearance of a mostly empty West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside that larger map is another showing smaller clusters or sub-races which the researchers picked up in finer detail. See: American blacks, Mormons, New York Jews, Amish, and Appalachistanis, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.springernature.com/full/springer-static/image/art%3A10.1038%2Fncomms14238/MediaObjects/41467_2017_Article_BFncomms14238_Fig3_HTML.jpg?as=webp&#34; alt=&#34;Distribution of ancestral birth locations in North America associated with IBD clusters.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fig. 3: &#34;Points show pedigree birth locations that are disproportionately assigned to each cluster. Only birth locations with OR&gt;x within indicated generations y–z are plotted, in which parameters x, y, z are chosen separately per cluster to better visualize the cluster&#39;s historical geographic concentration; full distributions of ancestral birth locations in the United States, Europe and worldwide are given in Supplementary Figs. 18–20. For each cluster, points are independently scaled by the number of pedigree annotations. See Fig. 2 and Table 1 for more details. Note that clusters are separated into two maps only for clarity. Also note that the concentration of Puerto Rican ancestors in Hawaii probably reflects their arrival there in the early 1900s (ref. 64).&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There we have it: the five largest genetic groups of America are New England &amp;amp; Utah, Pennsylvania/Ohio/New Jersey, Lower Midwest/Appalachia, Upper Mountain South, and Lower Coastal South. Most classic Americans come from one or some of these races. We can also see a pattern of settlement from America’s early days: the coastal population of the colonial South swept along the Gulf coast from the Carolinas along Florida, Alabama, to settle at the far end Louisiana and East Texas. Meanwhile the Appalachian South spread across the mountains to reach Tennessee, Arkansas, and eventually Central Texas. Early Virginians spread through the mountains to south Ohio and Indiana, meanwhile Pennsylvanians went to East Ohio and (what would later be) West Virginia (a newfound explanation for that state’s siding with the Union and breaking from VA? [but notice the small dot size, indicating almost equal settlement from each cluster]). And Michiganders belong with New Englanders, which coincides with well-known early Yankee migration in the 1820s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this map above we also get these charts showing mean locations for pedigree reports for each major group for hte last few generations. We can clearly see that even four generations ago, each group was heavily vertically stratified, and remains so to this day, but which has dispersed slightly as time went on; apparently “Go West Young Man” was taken as a maxim. Longitudinally, we can trace a clear western migration through the moving of the mean longitude and a dispersal through the movement of the horizontal bars. Now we have a time element for these migrations: coastal Southerners spread quickly along the Gulf Coast. One generation ago there was a great spreading across the country, possibly as historical populations centers and cities became unliveable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.springernature.com/full/springer-static/image/art%3A10.1038%2Fncomms14238/MediaObjects/41467_2017_Article_BFncomms14238_Fig5_HTML.jpg?as=webp&#34; alt=&#34;Five largest clusters predict North-South US geography across multiple generations&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fig. 5: &#34;In a, each circle gives the mean latitude (in degrees) of all pedigree birth location annotations within a given generation linked to genotypes assigned to each of the five clusters; end points of vertical bars represent 10th and 90th empirical percentiles. These statistics are compiled from pedigree annotations with US birth locations only. Note that ‘0 generations ago’ refers to genotyped individuals. For contrast, b shows the same statistics, but for longitude instead of latitude. Each degree of longitude or latitude is roughly equivalent to 100 km. Examples of US cities by latitude and longitude include Boston, MA (42.4, −71.1), New Orleans, LA (30.0, −90.1) and Sacramento, CA (38.6, −121.5).&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hidden in the Supplementary Material are the following spectral embedding analyses. These show divergence of each specialty cluster from the rest of the dataset, for example we can see the divergence of both Puerto Ricans and Jews from the main cluster. In figure (g) you can see a small divergence of Appalachistanis from the main genetic body. We can see that, for example, Northeast Mexicans and New Mexicans share some affinity, but are still dinstinct, possibly convergin in the Spanish Nuevomexicano population still living in New Mexico, which we will see later; or that Hawaiians and Colombians are about as divergent as possible. See how Acadians are contiguous with French Canadians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/SFig-4-1.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Supplemental Figure 4 a b c d&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/SFig-4-2.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Supplemental Figure 4 e f g h&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/SFig-4-3.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Supplemental Figure 4 i j k l&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin-bottom: 30px;&#34;&gt;Supp. Fig. 4: &#34;Clusters projected onto spectral embedding. Plots a, c, e, g, i, k show all 769,444 vertices in the completely connected network projected onto different dimensions of the spectral embedding. Samples are colored by membership to selected clusters, and by their assignment to a stable subset (Supplementary Data 2). Samples assigned to the same cluster and stable subset are shown as darker colored circles; samples assigned to the same cluster but not assigned to the stable subset are shown as lighter colored crosses; all other samples are shown as light gray circles.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/SFig-5-1.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Supplemental Figure 5 a b c d&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/SFig-5-2.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Supplemental Figure 5 e f g h&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/SFig-5-3.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34; title=&#34;Supplemental Figure 5 i j k l&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 5: &#34;Clusters projected onto subgraph spectral embedding. The subgraph is obtained by discarding vertices assigned to clusters containing stable subsets identified in the initial spectral embedding. Plots a, c, e, g, i show all 586,147 vertices in the subgraph projected onto different dimensions of the spectral embedding. Samples are colored by membership to selected clusters, and by their assignment to a stable subset (Supplementary Data 2).&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice also that Irish, Scandinavian, Mennonites, Amish etc. are separated in the table above and in the spectral embedding. Why is that? I thought Irish and Amish would be contiguous with mainline Americans? It’s not because they don’t make up a component of the American Race, but because in some areas they’ve remained so isolated it’s possible to draw them out from other clusters, as they are in these charts. See how we can draw out Utah Mormons from the mainline population in the same way, due to their isolation. These spectral analysis charts show how differentiated from the mean each ethnos goes: Jews and Africans are very distinct from Americans, while Scandinavians, Amish, Irish, and Mormons are distinct but not very divergent, most likely due to similar origin populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;Genetic-Origins&#34;&gt;Genetic Origins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Americans like to know their origins in the Old World. Let’s see some global admixture data on the groups presented here. See the column below ‘Global Admixture’ and see that most of the American population groups at the bottom are simply ‘Western European’. Specialty groups like Irish, Portuguese, Scandinavians can be pinned down to precise regions in Europe, but average Americans cannot be located so precisely. Later we will look into more finely grained origin maps to see exactly the regions in Europe that contribute admixture to the American genome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRma4r6WUAAj0_N.png&#34; alt=&#34;Global Admixture Table&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&#34;ACB, African Caribbean in Barbados; ASW, people with African Ancestry in Southwest USA; CEU, Utah residents with Northern and Western European ancestry; CLM, Colombians from Medellin, Colombia; FIN, Finnish in Finland; MXL, Mexican ancestry from Los Angeles; Nat. Am., Native American; PUR, Puerto Rican. Rows are grouped to coincide with the discussion. Admixture statistics are expressed as d&gt;x, Pin%, Pout%, meaning that Pin% individuals assigned to the cluster and Pout% outside the cluster have estimated admixture proportions for ancestral population d&gt;x. The ‘1000 Genomes’ column summarizes population labels of any 1000 Genomes samples that project onto the same stable subsets defined in spectral embedding.&#34; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is Western Europe here? How defined? Luckily the researchers provide us an answer in this map. It covers Madrid to Warsaw, and a sliver of southern England to include an English sample in that region. ‘Great Britain’ encloses all of the Netherlands and most of northern France, half of Ireland. Clearly these are genetic regions, not strict political borders, to account for similarities between neighbors, ancient migrations, etc. Thankfully in the Supplementary Material, they give us additional maps in fine geographic detail, which we will review later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRma-XfXMAAXeFQ.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Region Map&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRma_f9XMAAD0DH.png&#34; alt=&#34;Region Map Zoomed In&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&#34;Geographic regions corresponding to ancestral populations in global ancestry reference panel. See Supplementary Table 2 for composition the panel. Admixture proportions for these regions are collapsed into a single admixture proportion representing West Africa. Map and figure designed by AncestryDNA.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we are about to dive into a long series of maps going into extreme detail on the migratory patterns of these American sub-races. First, following the researchers, let’s examine a sub-race as practice: Cajuns, Acadians, and French Canadians. Blue dots are ancestors of modern Acadians/Cajuns, and magenta dots show ancestors of French Canadians/Québécois. See here how many Cajuns and Acadians list their ancestors from 1649 - 1791 as being born still in France, alongside those in Louisiana and French Canada. 1791, of course, is the year that Britain established &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower_Canada&#34;&gt;Lower Canada&lt;/a&gt;, which combined with the pressure of the French Revolution and the attractiveness of the new continent, spurred the settlement of Quebec. By 1878 we see most French Canadians had already arrived, and by 1962 many had moved to New England as well. Notice how between the 6-9th generations and the 3-5th generations, the large collection of blue dots had moved from Nova Scotia to Louisiana. This is due to the British &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expulsion_of_the_Acadians&#34;&gt;expulsion the Acadians from Nova Scotia&lt;/a&gt;, after which they took refuge in Louisiana. Notice that Cajun Louisiana does not show migration into the rest of the South, nor vice versa. French Louisiana has been an ethnic enclave for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.springernature.com/full/springer-static/image/art%3A10.1038%2Fncomms14238/MediaObjects/41467_2017_Article_BFncomms14238_Fig4_HTML.jpg?as=webp&#34; alt=&#34;Genealogical data traces origins of Cajuns/Acadians in Atlantic Canada (blue) and migration of French Canadians (magenta) to the US.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Fig. 4: &#34;Map locations are plotted if OR&gt;10 within the indicated range of pedigree generations (date ranges give the 5th and 95th percentiles of birth year annotations). Points are scaled by number of pedigree annotations, separately for each of the six maps. Note that not all current political borders are shown.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now here’s a map depicting the same thing for the entire American continent. You can see that at Generation 0 (the ones who participated in the DNA test), they coalesce around cities, but their parents fill out the countryside, as do their grandparents and great-grandparents. From nine generations ago to four generations ago, we have Manifest Destiny, a clear western migration over the centuries. But between four and three generations ago, corresponding to the announcement of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_frontier#End_of_the_frontier&#34;&gt;close of the American frontier&lt;/a&gt;, we see that westward settlement largely ceases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmepWAXwAIEh34.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Distribution of birth locations in continental US, by generation&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 16: &#34;Distribution of birth locations in continental US, by generation. Generation 0 corresponds to the DNA sample, so should reflect the birth location distribution of (present-day) US-born AncestryDNA customers. Generation 1 corresponds to parents, generation 2 corresponds to grandparents, and so on. Ancestral birth locations in each pedigree generation are divided into a grid, with grid points every 0.5 degrees of latitude and longitude. Only locations with at least 20 pedigree nodes are shown on the map. The size of each point is scaled by the number of annotated pedigree nodes at that location, separately for each generation.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are the American ancestors. But since many of America’s White ancestors came asynchronously over the last three centuries, the researchers also created a map of ancestral birthplaces in Europe based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://Ancestry.com&#34;&gt;Ancestry.com&lt;/a&gt; pedigree reporting. You can see that the English, Scotch, and Irish were always coming to America for the country’s entire history, Continental French and German immigration largely dried up two generations ago. But in the country’s earlier days, there was massive immigration from all Western European countries (save Spain, who had their own &lt;em&gt;hispanohablante&lt;/em&gt; countries to move to). French immigration seemingly slowed to a halt around five generations ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmesgDX0AYQpDL.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Distribution of birth locations in Europe, by generation&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 17: &#34;Distribution of birth locations in Europe, by generation.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also go into specific ancestries of the five major sub-races, and later of the smaller genetic clusters. Let’s begin with Pennsylvania, the Mid-Atlantic strain. But in these maps the odds-ratio (OR) becomes more significant, so it is worth making sure all readers understand what this value means. The dots are &lt;em&gt;colored&lt;/em&gt; according to their odds ratio, which shows “the proportion of ancestral birth locations [reported by] cluster members at that map location over the proportion [reported by] non-cluster members at the same location.” So if you see a blue dot in Middle Pennsylvania, indicating a high OR for that cluster, it &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; mean that that geographical area of PA is the main contributor of admixture to the Pennsylvania cluster, but that the people born in that location will more likely show up exclusively in the PA cluster, and not in other clusters. And people born elsewhere are less likely to appear in the Pennsylvania cluster. When dots get smaller in size, it shows a smaller OR value, indicating that people from that area can belong to one cluster or the other in almost equal proportions. Britain, for example, has large dots here, indicating a large contribution to the PA admixture. But other clusters also report British ancestry, so the dots are &lt;em&gt;not exclusive&lt;/em&gt; to PA, which prevents them from being red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we know that early in Pennsylvania’s history, it was settled by large numbers of Germans (50,000 settled in 1760 alone). This is reflected in Germany’s large dots (lots of ancestral birthplaces) and relatively high OR value (the ancestors born there went largely to PA). The Pennsylvanian race comes primarily from Britain and Germany, and secondly from around Western and Northern Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRme3pPWYAICwu5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Distribution of ancestral birth locations worldwide, in North America, and in Europe, for each cluster detected in an IBD sub-network.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 19b &#34;Pennsylvania&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine the Northeast and Utah cluster. There are actually two maps here: one centered on New England, and one on Utah. New England shows large migrations from Britain, Ireland, and Germany, but also that many of the immigrants from all over Europe came to N.E. alone. As expected, because people weren’t migrating to Lexington or Savannah, but to New York or Boston, or somewhere near those cities. For example, the red dots in Norway indicate that many Norweigian immigrants now cluster with the Northeast group, which is reflected in both New York and the obscure Norweigian communities of Passaic and Sussex county New Jersey. (We will see later about Norweigian migration to the Midwest, in which more of Norway is shown with high OR. What we see here seems to be exclusive immigration from certain villages, likely following family). The Northeast, then, after receiving waves of immigration into its cities, is a wide mixture of all Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Utah is a different story. The Utahians report their ancestry coming from New England, England proper, and Denmark. Few came directly from England to Utah, but rather represent the last holdout of the ethnically pure English populations of colonial New England. Utah and its Danish component will be revisited later as we review enclave races.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmfNv5XoAAseh6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Distribution of ancestral birth locations worldwide, in North America, and in Europe, for each cluster detected in an IBD sub-network.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 18a&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmfPdFXwAMAYz9.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Distribution of ancestral birth locations worldwide, in North America, and in Europe, for each cluster detected in an IBD sub-network.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 19a&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the following regions, unless otherwise stated, they derive ancestry from those six colonial nations listed above: England, Germany, Scotland, Ireland, France, the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmfiBcWUAAgmjb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;The-South-as-a-Whole&#34;&gt;The South as a Whole&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most Southerners only trace their ancestry to other parts of the South, not to Europe. This indicates that the South was not a destination of later European migrants, but remained the home of the original colonists, although you can see that some Mid-Atlantic colonists are represented here. In Europe they trace broadly across the continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmfpS2WUAEsOk3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 18b&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;The-Upper-South&#34;&gt;The Upper South&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This region encompasses the westward expansion of Virginia into Tennessee, across Arkansas and Oklahoma, and into Texas. They again primarily trace ancestry to themselves, but unlike the Lower South we see moderate immigration from the six European nations and from across the US. Many from the Western Carolinas still live along this path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmfxexXsAIUdam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 19i&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;The-Lower-South&#34;&gt;The Lower South&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the coastal Carolinas, these settlers swept along Florida, Alabama, and Mississippi into Eastern Texas. In 1814, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creek_War#Results&#34;&gt;the Creek Indians were expelled&lt;/a&gt; or forced to give up land, the opening-up of this territory and “Alabama Fever” gripped many South Carolinans which caused them to move in. A similar migration occurred in 1820-30s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/articles/history-archaeology/cherokee-removal/&#34;&gt;Georgia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seminole_Wars#First_Seminole_War&#34;&gt;Florida&lt;/a&gt; when Indians were expelled and Whites took their place. Notice again the separation between Anglo Louisiana and French Louisiana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmgIOqWYAERqMf.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 19j&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Appalachia&#34;&gt;Appalachia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most Appalachians trace their ancestry only to Appalachia, showing great insulation (whom I call &lt;em&gt;Appalachistani&lt;/em&gt;’s for their lack of outside admixture). Those who go to the Appalachians, evidently stay there, with some dispersion around the Lower Midwest. This region forms almost an ethnostate centered around the Cumberland Mountains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmg_DoXoAE0KQS.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 18h&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we leave the South, we also are given maps showing how each of these regions expanded from the original colonies into the American continent, in even greater detail than we’ve seen so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmhINdXoAEol2z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 27a&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmhJvQXwAA2zeG.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 27b&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmhLDmWYAYHfK_.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 27c&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will now delve into the smaller and more exclusive micro-races of the United States. Some are noticeable, some are hidden; some try to maintain an ethnostate, some are isolated by lifestyle alone. Either way, they are identifiably different from the five main sub-races.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Mormons&#34;&gt;Mormons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best known group, those settlers which formed a new religion and set off to Utah are still the prime inhabitants of that western land. Additionally, a large number of Mormons descend from (mainly Midland and West) England, Scotland around Edinburgh, and from Denmark. Most Danes migrated &lt;em&gt;exclusively&lt;/em&gt; into Mormon communities and nowhere else in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmgj1gXIAESuWs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 20a&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also trace the movement of the Mormons through maps like the one below, which shows where the ancestors of modern Mormons were born generations ago. Overall, Mormons are members of the old New England sub-race, but simply isolated out west, insulated by both religion/lifestyle and geography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmg8e9XIAoN_IR.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Genealogical data by generation trace US migration and European origins of Utah cluster&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 24: &#34;Genealogical data by generation trace US migration and European origins of Utah cluster. The size of each point is scaled by number of pedigree birth location annotations, separately for each of the 6 maps. Date ranges are the 5th and 95th percentiles of the birth year annotations&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;The-Amish&#34;&gt;The Amish&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Amish of PA, NY, and OH, primarily trace their heritage to those same states (very heavily to certain areas), but also to Western Germany and Switzerland, as Amish people themselves will tell you of their Swiss heritage, genetically and in their religious traditions. In fact, it seems like all immigrants from near Bern, Switzerland became Amish. The discrete nature of their settlements in America (i.e. Amish people tested report parentage from only specific communities) belies their peculiar rural lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmhUCeXwAETBi3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 20b&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;The-Irish&#34;&gt;The Irish&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Irish have dispersed most heavily around the Northeast, but in some areas they remained so overwhelming that they are still detectable, as in Chicago and in Nova Scotia. In other places, like Massachusetts, they’ve assimilated quite well with other Whites. You can see a number of Irish, or perhaps we should include the Scots by saying “Gaelic”, related people in Nove Scotia as well due to British colonization of the island in the colonial era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmhde9WYAcv25u.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 20c &#34;All Ireland&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, this study breaks down the American spread of Irish genes by region of Ireland: North, South, and West. The result, though, is a quite even spread regardless of region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmh6E9XwAEgq-p.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 26f &#34;South Ireland / Munster&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmh7Q9X0AAYh0Z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 26h &#34;West Ireland / Connaught&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmiJjkWQAYz3p5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 26g &#34;North Ireland / Ulster&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Scandinavians-and-Finns&#34;&gt;Scandinavians and Finns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the Vikings of the Midwest. Almost all settlers from Norway, Finland, Poland and most from Sweden, went straight to Wisconsin, Minnesota, and North Dakota, along with some settling in the more developed Northeast as mentioned earlier. It appears that Scandinavian supremacy is so complete in that part of the Midwest that Minnesota is simply Norse clay, and Iowa may be Swedish clay too. The red dots show that few other ethnicities exist there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmiPxPWYAMLp86.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 20d&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmiQ0CXIAI9Cy7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 26e&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmiTOLXIAEqtRL.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 19d&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Nuevos-Mexicanos&#34;&gt;Nuevos Mexicanos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Descended from the European Spanish settlers of New Mexico territory, this enclave makes up the primary ancestry of New Mexican ethnos. These are not Mexicans, but have been here since the Spanish settlement along the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camino_Real_de_Tierra_Adentro&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Camino Real de Tierra Adentro&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; trail since 1598, which you can actually trace based on the settlement pattern shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmigGDXoAEsK3R.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 19n&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmil8PXwAE_w_Z.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Camino Real de Tierra Adentro, http://visitdurango.mx/cultura-e-historia/&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Mennonites&#34;&gt;Mennonites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sparse community began through homesteading on the Great Plains in the 1800s, and now find themselves centered around Kansas, Oklahoma, and Nebraska. They come England, Scotland, Germany, and exclusively from East Germany and parts of Sweden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmjAjRX0AMLOUm.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 19g&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;French-Canadians-and-Acadians&#34;&gt;French Canadians and Acadians&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though this group was our example, it is worth revisiting them. The piece of Quebec attached to NE is occupied by Frenchmen of every region, from the English Channel to the Mediterranean. Acadians are those French of Nova Scotia and Louisiana. They hold all of Southern LA, and the southern tips of MS and AL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmjMhoWQAUxSXD.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 19e&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmjVn6XEAI7XQ1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 20f&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmjfgyXsAIzoLn.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 20g&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Appalachians&#34;&gt;Appalachians&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though we’ve already seen the Cumberland Appalachians, the researchers bring them up again because they stand out at every level of detail as a total ethnostate. They report almost no ancestry anywhere but within Appalachia or the Chesapeake Bay, even 9 generations back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmjjovWUAEYW0E.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 20h&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Scots&#34;&gt;Scots&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separate from the Scotch-Irish of Appalachia and the Highland Scots elsewhere in America, the Scots as a cluster show up linked to Nova Scotia and the Atlantic Islands in Canada, along with the Toronto area of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmjoQVXsAI5aRE.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 26i&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Italians&#34;&gt;Italians&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The famous Italians of NY/NJ. The Italians have not spread far, regardless of region of origin they have mostly stayed in the New York City area or in nearby states of the Northeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRnFJhOXoAc1R00.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 26j&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;!------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we are given admixture analyses for all groups at all levels of detail. You can see that for White Americans, admixture comes from Britain, Ireland, Scandinavia, and Western Europe. The insinuation that some people make that Whites all have a black or Indian ancestor is a lie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/SFig-9.png&#34; class=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 9: &#34;Admixture proportions in top-level IBD network clusters. Filled circles correspond to mean admixture proportions, and error bars give [0.05,0.95] credible intervals.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/AmericanGenetics/SFig-11.jpg&#34; class=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 10: &#34;Admixture proportions in IBD sub-network clusters. Filled circles correspond to mean admixture proportions, and error bars give [0.05,0.95] credible intervals.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmlBEXXwAASpCo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Supp. Fig. 11: &#34;Admixture proportions in stable subsets identified from spectral analysis. Filled circles correspond to mean admixture proportions, and error bars give [0.05,0.95] credible intervals.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;Conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I truly recommend coming back to the three charts above to prove or disprove any racial admixture in the American population, they’re quite good. And once again I urge you to read the paper itself, either to get a better understanding of the results, or to find one of the many extra groups in the Supplementary Material which I haven’t covered. We’ve discussed a lot of smaller races, but again I’d like to reiterate that, as shown above, the predominant substrate in American Whites is England, Wales, Scotland. Secondary admixtures: Irish, German, Scandinavian, French. Many people who came over after the Revolution were of the same original race as the earliest settlers, and blended in completely in a short time. I personally don’t take “length of time in America” as a determinant factor towards Americanness from a genetics standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/FRmkx8lXwAEo9KR.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Tweet Image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <updated>2022-04-30T11:11:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>https://uisneac.com/Religion-Across-the-Aions/</id>
        <title>Religion Across the Aions</title>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://uisneac.com/Religion-Across-the-Aions/"/>
        <content type="html">&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-style-marker&#34; href=&#34;/assets/css/APlayer.min.css&#34;&gt;&lt;script src=&#34;/assets/js/APlayer.min.js&#34; class=&#34;aplayer-secondary-script-marker&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Menhir.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s remember the concept of Aions. An Aion is very similar to a Yuga, but derived from Hellennic and Indo-European astrology and the procession of the equinox rather than a division of the eternal cycle into four descending sections. The movement of the Earth’s axis over time causes the constellations to drift slowly with respect to the Earth, specifically the spring horizon. When Hipparchus discovered this c. 150 BC, the spring equinox sun sat in front of Aries; by 1000 AD, it sat well in front of Pisces. And so the very stars themselves change precedence over us. Choosing the spring equinox was somewhat arbitrary, but choose any astronomical point and the stars behind it will drift. Since the stars hold gentle influence over our lives, our minds, and our stories, the changing of the stars also changes the nature of the world itself. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/ogmios/status/1392592990393229317&#34;&gt;this book&lt;/a&gt; for a breakdown of ancient star-wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This point cannot be overstated: different aions have different rulers, just as the stars do. One aion will not be the same as any other. What is Right and Good in one, will be Boring, Tired, Ineffective in another. We can even say that they have different rules. Another point about the astronomy of this: many people divide the sky into twelve &lt;em&gt;equal&lt;/em&gt; sections, instead of dividing then based on where the constellations end. Any Astrology based on math rather than naked-eye observations is inferior, speaking anthropologically. Research Tropical vs Sidereal systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Stars.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/AionChart.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with one we all know. When the stars of Aries were presiding, the world was led by the Aries archetype. This aion stretched from roughly 2000 BC to 0 AD. During this time the Ram, not the Bull or the Fishes, was the primary world archetype. The Ram meant that the actions of all the people of the world were characterized by pushing, creating boundaries, and challenging. Force itself was king. See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/ogmios/status/1402068975740243969&#34;&gt;hidden meaning of the Celtic Ram&lt;/a&gt;. And what major events did the world see during the reign of the Ram? The first division of the world into empires. And the two crowning achievements of the Age, Alexander’s Empire and Rome’s Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Babylon.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Babylonian Empire&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Alexander.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Alexander&#39;s Empire&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Rome.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Roman Empire&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In those days, it paid to be expansionist and violent. The primary archetype of that age was Achilles, who noticeably gained no land, but rather paved the way for other diplomats to take the land he conquered. If Achilles was born in 1500AD, his same actions would never work. Because the conditions of society in 1500 AD or 3500 BC were inappropriate for Achilles’ warlike nature. The time was not proper for a pure berserker like him. The Ram was the driving force behind the expansion of centralized political states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now compare this aion to the Aion of Taurus. The Bull is not forceful like the Ram, but he symbolizes wealth and stable sovereignty. A person with Sun in Taurus prefers to enjoy his winnings and to conquer power centers rather than enforce borders. What could be a major event of the Taurean Age? The Bronze Age Expansions of course, among the proto-Indo-Europeans, the proto-Semites, the Bantus at the very end, etc. Yet, these peoples never established political control as their descendants did in the Arian Age. The lack of central authority allowed the growth on thousands of local city states, as we see most iconically in Sumer and Babylon, but also in, for example, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://balkhandshambhala.blogspot.com/2012/10/bactria-land-of-thousand-cities.html&#34;&gt;Bactria-Margiana Archaeological Complex&lt;/a&gt;, the “land of a thousand cities.” Think of Conan the Barbarian as the archetypal Taurean warrior: traversing vast distances to strike down an evil central figure and to take rule of the city. Think of Gilgamesh, who was King of Ur, or Agamemnon, who, in the Arian Age myth, was usurped by the Arian Hero. The contrast throughout the Iliad between Agamemnon and Achilles is the dual energies of the Taurean warrior and the Arian warrior. The one wants to revel in his riches at the expense of honor, and wants the city. The other seeks honor and battle death, not material wealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/IE-Expansion.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Indo-European Expansion Map&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Agamemnon.webp&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, there is a Taruean aesthetic in the contruction of forts and religious temples during the Taurean Aion. &lt;a href=&#34;https://rgdn.info/en/nyugreyndzh_-_nasledie_druidov&#34;&gt;Newgrange&lt;/a&gt;, built by the Dagda, who is sometimes literally a bull; the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ancient-origins.net/ancient-places-asia/white-temple-and-great-ziggurat-mesopotamian-city-uruk-006835&#34;&gt;White Temple of Uruk&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;https://pk-photography.blogspot.com/2011/06/mohenjo-daro.html&#34;&gt;Mohenjo Daro&lt;/a&gt;; singular, glorious temples and cities. Let’s compare these to art and artifacts of the Arian Age: pottery, below from 1300 BC, horses and war chariots; the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thearchaeologist.org/blog/treasury-of-atreus-the-monumental-mycenaean-tomb&#34;&gt;Treasury of Atreus&lt;/a&gt;, Mycenae; most steppe and early European &lt;a href=&#34;https://minervamagazine.com/treasures-of-the-scythian-kings.html&#34;&gt;burial mounds&lt;/a&gt; were formed in this aion, richly adorned and scattered across the lands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Pottery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movement from Taurus to Aries brought us the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mysterium.com/eighthgate.html&#34;&gt;Mithraic Tauroctony&lt;/a&gt; (notice: the Zodiac above Mithras). The transition caused Moses to reject the Golden Cow (notice: gold, wealth, Taurean symbols) in favor of the forceful God of Fire. A Mosaic Tauroctony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/MosesSerpent.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;http://amortalperspectiveofeternity.blogspot.com/2012/03/moses-and-brass-serpent.html&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Moses and the Brass Serpent by Judith Mehr&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s go back further. Before Taurus the world was in Gemini, approx. 6,000 - 4,000 BC. We have little to no direct mythical evidence of the Geminian Age, except for echoes in myths written in later Ages, but archaeology has given us a solid idea of what the world was like then. Most of Europe was settled by Anatolian Farmers within this Aion. This was when Mercury/Lugh/Wotan taught our ancestors farming, craft skills, and writing. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.prehistory.it/ftp/inventory/danube_script/danube_script_01.htm&#34;&gt;Vinča Script&lt;/a&gt;, the world’s earliest letters, dates from about 5000 BC. Gemini is ruled by the planet Mercury, and the Twins of Gemini reflect this. The Twins are an echo of a myth which was surely the dominant world-archetype in the Geminian Aion. They are Castor and Pollux to the Greeks. Pollux was the soul of Castor, both sons of Zeus and of Tyndareus of Sparta (or in other versions, one was the son of immortal Zeus and the other of mortal Tyndareus). In Babylon, the Twins are Meshlamtaea and Lugalirra (Lugh?), which mean “One who has arisen from the Underworld” (Otherworld?) and “Mighty King”. That is, one is “dead” or a spirit, and one is a King or at least royalty. Both are associated with a god of sickness and health. We can therefore expect that the Geminian Aion is that era in which Man first discovered his soul as separate from his own being, or his Self as separate from his Ego. One dies, one never dies. One can be King, one is only a spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it mean that Man’s soul first became separate from himself? Man first became self-aware at this time. He started on the path of becoming an individual rather than an extension of the tribe. It was the birth of consciousness, hence why the Bible dates Genesis to this time. Before that time, in the Cancerian Aion specifically, Man was merely a finger of the tribal hand, an appendage of the racial arm. By developing his conscious mind, as opposed to his collective, unconscious mind, he began writing, planning for agriculture, trading, and thinking. And the trade of ideas between peoples and within the mind was mirrored by trading routes between the first cities. Communication as well. The cities of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vision.org/de/node/161&#34;&gt;Eridu&lt;/a&gt;, Aleppo, &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.com/books?id=TSLeX0GRNqwC&amp;amp;q=121#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=7%2C000%20years%20of%20a%20settled%20community&amp;amp;f=false&#34;&gt;Argos&lt;/a&gt; (which introduced standard weights to Greece), and Athens were first inhabited under the stars of Gemini. The myth of the birth of the Dioscuri is arguably a myth of the transition from Gemini to Taurus, as the Taurean God Zeus eventually sent the Twins to live in the stars. One of Athens’ most ancient temples is dedicated to the Dioscuri.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Eridu.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Eridu&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cancerian Aion, c. 8,000 - 6,000 BC, the time of the Great Mother, in which Man first began to coagulate into permanent villages. The Mother archetype which ruled this Aion was what inspired man to form homes and establish family life. As we go back further, we have fewer and fewer myths, as well as far less material evidence. I can’t point to a single anti-Mother myth which signals the end of Cancer and the beginning of Gemini, but the archetype is certainly there. Gaia’s sons, Rhea’s sons, etc. The most appropriate, perhaps, is Leto, who birthed the divine siblings Artemis and Apollo. Quite literally a mythic mother figure giving way to her two divine children. The state of the world in the Cancerian Aion was the first major step away from nomadic hunting and gathering. Many peoples supplemented their game with crops, and build solid houses for the first time. (Structures are dated prior this age, but they increased their range here). I want to emphasize: we have an aversion to “The Feminine” now which is unfounded. There is a time and a place for feminine energy, just like all things, and in the Cancerian Aion “feminine” actions would make you powerful. Actions like building a house and defending it. The question is whether we need feminine energy today, or masculine. And the answer is both and neither, we apply them selectively at one time or another. In other words, it’s up to you, and the spirit of the age will guide you. The Aion of Cancer was likely also the first time Man consciously discovered the workings of Woman’s pregnancy, that it wasn’t some supernatural act but that it had a cause and effect. Many other sexual lessons likely emerged in these two thousand years, for both parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And earliest, the Aion of Leo, from c. 10,000 BC to 8,000 BC when the Sun rose into the Lion constellation on the spring equinox. Directly succeeding the last glacial maximum, the Aion of Leo was a time of bold leaders and actors, unconcerned with personal loss or homes. A majority of the world was still hunter-gatherers: this was the mythical Golden Age. Man was yet undivided from the tribe, and acted as an extension of the group. For this reason, with the world warming again, each band of men took leaders to roam the world and win what prizes could be won. The lion brings with it the waters of glacial ice melt, which show that through daring and action the world can be enriched. Leo, ruled by the Sun, showed Man to strive for something greater than mere survival. We cannot say much more about this time, because even in archeology the lights are dim. Göbekli Tepe was built in Turkey, and Star Carr was inhabited in Yorkshire. There is a popular perception that people then were less inteligent or capable only of milling about the village’s mud houses, but directional social organization was a new phenomenon. Without being constrained by the frozen environment, our ancestors were allowed to take bold actions in a new way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Leo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Aion of Leo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In roughly 0 AD we passed from Aries into Pisces, this is the transition people still argue over. Our world shifted from a priority of force (which was good in its time) to one of mercy and grace (which is coming to an end soon). This isn’t to say that force became unnecessary, remember that we’re speaking of the permutations of the soul here, and its fascinations. Jesus showed our ancestors their latent fascination with goodness, purity, and sanctity over dominance. The Two Fishes, as opposed to the Ram, signified the divergence of Good and Evil. The serpent as a symbol was and is hated by Piscean Man, but welcomed as a scion of wisdom by Arian and Taurean Man. Is it any coincidence that the East with Buddhism and the West with Christianity converted to new religions centered on very similar figures, with very similar practices when compared to the Arian paganisms they replaced? The nature of the world was changing. Plenty of symbolism points to the shift from an Aries Aion to a Pisces Aion. Jesus appears as a slain lamb (Ram), for example, one of his christograms is a fish, his apostles are “fishers of men”, and his dark counterpart in the figure of Satan, who is the second fish of Pisces. And this should make sense. The Romans had mastered life in the Arian Age, become the best warriors and empire builders. If the world hadn’t changed, human life would have stultified under the immortal and bloated Roman Empire. God struck down the serpent which was holding back the waters of change, and the world shifted again. This is his plan for mankind, and Europa specifically, prewritten in the stars and he dislikes when people defy his plan, hence why the reactionary movement to return to an agrarian world which ended centuries ago will fail. The pseudo-reactionary movement to build a new world on top of the wisdom of the old world will succeed. No one can reverse turning of the heavens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are moving into into Aquarian Aion, from roughly 2000 AD to 4000 AD. People debate on when it really begins, but I believe it began in the 60s, and the transition period will last until the 2140s. We have both Piscean and Aquarian energy in the world right now. The Age of Aquarius will be characterized by a longing for wisdom, likely caused by a forgetfulness of the past and tradition. Aquarius is the countersign of Leo, and the halfway point around the Great Year of 26,000 years. So I theorize that the next 6 aions will be spent consciously rediscovering all the truths and esoteric sciences which were lost in the past 12,000 years. We will once again understand the body, the mind, and the spirit, and be able to navigate our world in strength and virtue. Aquarius as the countersign of Leo also indicates that everything lacking in the Aion of Leo will occur in overabundance in the Aion of Aquarius. Every sign has their countersign, and also occurs in a fractal nature. Every year the sun travels through these signs; every month, the moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking this astrological view allows us to understand the triumph of Christianity over paganism. Both are appropriate only for their times. The resurgence of pagan, or “non-Christian” ideas, in our time is the dawning of the Aquarian quest for wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/Religion-Across-the-Aions/Aquarius.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Aquarian Aion Art&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
        <category term="Religion" />
        <category term="Astrology" />
        <updated>2021-10-02T11:41:00.000Z</updated>
    </entry>
</feed>
